Using Xiaoboda to enhance citizens' digital resilience through tools and communities
以小伯大透過工具還有社群來提升公民的數位韌性
It is a great honor to have this opportunity to make an opening here today
非常榮幸今天有這個機會到這邊做一個開場
Then I remember that in the planning of our lecture topics in the first two sessions
那我記得在前兩場我們的講題規劃當中
We compare the so-called digital resilience issue from the national level
我們比較從國家的層面來看所謂的數位韌性的課題
Let's talk about it, I remember we talked about
那我們討論 我記得我們當時討論的
Probably a resilience in terms of infrastructure, communications infrastructure
大概是基礎設施 通訊基礎設施方面的一個韌性
how to do it
要如何去做實現
So when we talk about oceans, when we talk about satellites, when we talk about war
所以我們談到海濫 談到衛星 談到戰爭的時候
What are the alternatives and what has the government done to prepare?
還有哪些替代方案 還有政府已經做了哪些籌備的工作
Then I think we will also talk about digital resilience in today's session
那我想今天的場次我們也談數位韌性
But we landed today we landed today
不過我們今天落地了 我們今天落地了
So what we're going to discuss today is
那我們今天要探討的是
Every citizen at the time of this possible disaster
每一位公民到底在這個可能的災難發生的時候
or the moment when there may be a war situation in the future
或未來可能有戰爭情況發生的當下
whether before, during or after
不管是在之前當中或之後
what can we do
我們可以做些什麼事情
To build a digital resilience that belongs to this citizen
來建構一個屬於這個公民的一個數位韌性
Jiang Tang is also very honored for this event
那蔣唐這個場次也非常榮幸
We have invited the Digital Diplomacy Association to be our partner in this
我們邀請到數位外交協會擔任我們的這個合作夥伴
Then I think the Digital Diplomacy Association has been
那我想這個數位外交協會在過去幾個月當中
They're in the middle of this war in Ukraine
他們在這個烏克蘭的戰爭當中
They also made quite a bit of an observation related to this
他們也做了相當多的這個相關的一個觀察
Then I want to cheer up and wait for it to be included in his sharing.
那我想加油等一下會在他的這個分享當中
Let me give you a more detailed introduction
跟大家做一個更細部的一個介紹
Well I think we're happy with this today
那我想我們今天的這個我們很高興
Today we invite this very grassroots group
今天邀請到非常屬於草根性的這個團體
whether citizen group media
不管是公民團體媒體
Or a representative of this tech community or startup
或者是這個技術社群或者新創公司的代表
Come to share with you such a topic
來跟大家做這樣的一個議題分享
Then I think I will first introduce our host for this session
那我想我就先首先來介紹我們這個場次的主持人
Then for this session we invited this crap Red National Army Chief Operating Officer
那這個場次我們邀請到的是這個臥槽的紅國軍營運長
The chief operating officer of the National Army used to be the editor-in-chief of the shit
那國軍營運長過去也擔任過臥槽的總編輯
And then there's this Citizens Watch, director of policy at the Congressional Coalition
然後還有這個公民監督國會聯盟政策部的主任
Then he also participated in editing this shit
那他同時也參與編輯過這個臥槽的
The Civic Action Guide published a while ago
前陣子出版的公民行動指南
I also make a small recommendation here
我這邊也做一個小小推薦
In fact, it is really worth buying the basics
其實真的很值得下手買基本
By the way, buy more and give them to relatives and friends
順便多買基本送給親朋好友
I think I'll put the time behind
我想我就把後面的時間
Give it to our military operations chief
交給我們的國軍營運長
The chief operating officer will leave it to you
營運長就交給您了
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you for the introduction
謝謝主持人介紹
and today's guests
還有今天各位來賓
There are also friends from the media participating
還有媒體朋友的參加
I didn't think the host would follow the opening
沒有想主持人有跟開場
help us lose first
先幫我們打輸
but this is embarrassing
但這個很不好意思
But I think this is a private unit
但是就是我覺得這個是民間單位
Different from government departments
跟政府部門也不一樣的地方
I think it's a
我覺得這是一個
Just mentioned a good opening
剛剛前面提到一個很好的開場
Like today, I also invited many friends from non-governmental organizations
像今天也邀請到很多來自民間單位的朋友
I think we do things differently
我覺得我們雖然做的事情不一樣
but to some extent
但是某些程度
we just see the same problem
我們就是看到了同樣的問題
some things are
有些事情就是
We feel like someone should do it
這我們覺得好像應該有人要做
but no one does
卻沒有人做
we might feel like saying
我們可能會覺得說
this thing maybe
這個事情也許
big business to do
大企業要做
Maybe the government department will do
也許政府部門要做
maybe some people are going to come out and do it
也許有些人要出來做
But we may find ourselves saying
但是我們可能自己會發現說
Eh, it seems that when no one comes out to do it
欸 好像沒有人出來做的時候
we need to know
我們自己就要知道說
well you're the one who doesn't
好 你就是那個沒有人
we're going to act like no one
我們就要當那個沒有人去
do this first
把這個事情先做出來
Start small
先從小規模的做出來
After letting other government departments see
讓其他政府部門看到之後
Willingness is to use more resources to invest
願意就是用更大的資源去投入
make this thing better
讓這個事情能夠做得更好
Then of course we will talk about this topic today
那當然我們今天會講這個主題
I think it's still going back to saying something like
我想還是會回到說像
Ukrainian city of Russia
烏克蘭 俄羅斯都心
Ukraine has been more than a year
烏克蘭已經一年多了
That doesn't look like it's going to stop yet.
那目前看起來也沒有停止的跡象
Many people will compare
那很多人會去比較說
Some people say that Taiwan and Ukraine
台灣跟烏克蘭 有人說
Hey, Taiwan looks a lot like Ukraine
欸 台灣跟烏克蘭好像很像
But some people say that Taiwan is very different from Ukraine
但也有人說台灣跟烏克蘭很不一樣
Both are right, there are differences
也都對 也都有不一樣的地方
how to say
那怎麼說呢
In fact, we see Ukraine
其實我們看到烏克蘭
this is able to block
這是能夠擋下
This Russian Wu Qing
這個俄羅斯烏清
A very important key is to
很重要的一個關鍵是在於
It is the power of their democratization
就是他們的民進的力量
able to play out
能夠發揮出來
Not just the strength of the army
不只是軍隊的力量而已
Their democrat morale has improved enough
他們的民進士氣是有提升足以
To Party Under Russia's Invasion
以黨下俄羅斯的入侵
This reminds us of one thing
這回頭讓我們想到一件事情
That is to say, we used to lie on the grass and make some
就是說我們曾經臥草在做一些
Civilian interviews, when it comes to defense-related topics
民訪啊 國防相關專題的時候
A scholar put forward a very important concept
有一個學者提出一個很重要的概念
I think this is a
我覺得這個是一個
Today we're going to be here on this topic
今天大家會在這裡投入這個主題
a very important reason
一個很重要的原因
He said war, defense of Taiwan
他說戰爭 防衛台灣
this matter is too important
這個事情太重要
so that what not to just give
以至於什麼 以至於不能只交給
Ministry of Defense
國防部
what does this story tell us
這個故事告訴我們什麼
Today's government departments may generally think of saying
今天政府部門 我們可能一般想到說
Who will be responsible if there is a war
如果發生戰爭 那誰要負責
The Ministry of Defense, the barracks are going to be responsible
國防部啊 軍營要去負責
Actually not only, not only the Ministry of Defense
其實不只 不只國防部
departments of government like
政府的各個部門 就像
This chef is very
這個廚師很前面提到的
In fact, many government agencies are responsible for
其實非常多的政府單位都要負責
Protection of Critical Records Facilities
關鍵紀錄設施的防護
Maybe the Ministry of Health and Welfare, the Ministry of Transportation, the Ministry of the Interior, etc.
也許衛福部啊 交通部啊 內政部等等
to join the government
都要一起加入政府部門的
overall defense
整體的防衛
Is it the government's responsibility?
政府部門負責而已嘛
Not really
不盡然
Folks are also important
民間也很重要
How civil groups and individuals
如何民間的團體 個人
The power of the grassroots
上的發揮 草根的力量
Improve the defense of Taiwan as a whole
提升整體台灣的防衛
very dangerous
很危險性
This is how to keep
這也是如何能夠守下
A key to field aggression
外地侵略的一個關鍵
and we also know that
而且我們也知道就是
People often say that masters are among the people
大家常常講高手在民間
Does it mean that the government department
就是不是說政府部門
sometimes unwilling to do things
有時候不願意做事
Or they are lazy
或者說他們這個偷懶
or something
或者什麼的
Sometimes some ideas belong to government departments
有時候有些idea是政府部門的東西
did not think of
沒有想到
Our folk role is to test
我們民間的角色就是要去試劑一下
give them something different
給他們一些不一樣的想法
let them know say
讓他們知道說
It turns out that some problems can be solved like this
原來有些問題可以這樣被解決
So today of course I am today
所以今天當然我今天
responsible for hosting
負責主持
but it doesn't mean
但不代表就是說
This is the most powerful
這個是能夠最厲害的
I think the next few guests
我覺得接下來幾位來賓
Actually a very good one
其實都是非常好的一個
speakers they are many good
講者他們很多很好
I can share with you today
今天可以跟大家分享
How to Citizenship Tech
如何公民科技
can be used in this corner of our defense of Taiwan
能夠在我們防衛台灣的這個角
this plays an important role
這扮演很重要的角色
Then let me briefly introduce a few speakers
那我先簡單介紹幾位講者
that one is the president of the country
那一個是國家理事長
Of course, everyone should go through
那當然就是大家應該經過
Sugui Diplomatic Association
蘇貴外交協會
In fact, in recent years
其實在這幾年來
in online communities
在網路社群上
Helped Taiwan to do a lot of things
幫台灣發生做了很多事情
let more people know
讓更多人認識
Taiwan's Dilemma Internationally
台灣在國際上的困境
and then we
然後還有我們
What can we do to everyone in the international community
在國際社會上能夠對大家做什麼
It is Taiwan Can Help Taiwan Is Helping
就是台灣Can Help 台灣Is Helping
Give full play to the visibility of everyone in Taiwan and in the world
發揮讓大家在台灣在國際的能見度
Then there is our founder Xu Wulong
那再來還有就是我們的徐武龍這個創辦人
It’s also called Haba in reverse, right?
也是江湖逆稱是叫做哈霸嘛 對不對
It's that he's actually been a citizen tech all along.
就是他其實一直以來都是公民科技
We all call it through some hikes
我們就都叫做透過一些hike
Some technology and engineering methods allow everyone to participate in politics
一些科技工程的方式讓大家去參與政治
like if i'm not mistaken
像如果我印象沒有錯的話
There was an important one before
之前有一個很重要
and also an interesting project
而且也很有意思的專案
air box
叫做空氣盒子
How to let everyone use the power of the people
就如何讓大家用民間的力量
to let everyone know
去讓大家了解說
How is the air quality in all parts of Taiwan?
原來台灣全台灣各地空氣品質怎麼樣
This is a grassroots force from the bottom up
這是由下而上的一個草根力量
You can also urge the government to make some policy changes
也可以去督促政府做一些政策上的改變
Then come to the end, of course he still has this director Cai Wencheng Q-SURGE
那再來最後他當然還有這個蔡文成總監Q-SURGE
I think this thing does not matter whether it is a figure in the industry or a politician
我想這個東西不管是業界或是政界的人物
know the tool very well.
都非常了解這個工具
We can use this Q-SURGE to understand
我們可以透過這Q-SURGE去了解
What's going on in the community right now?
到底現在社群上面發生什麼事
This matter may not be used anymore
這個事情不一定可以再用在說
in business or in our political situation
商業上或是我們在政局
this mastery of entertainment
娛樂的這個掌握
Another very important thing is
還有一個很重要的是
In addition to shooting and setting up guns in modern warfare
現代戰爭除了開槍 搭炮以外
community fake news
社群的假訊息
can also play an important role
也可以扮演很重要的角色
i want to wait maybe
我想等一下可能
The director will also share with us
這個總監也會跟我們來分享說
What kind of help can Q-Sage provide here?
到底Q-Sage可以在這邊提供什麼樣的幫助
then we first we first
那我們首先我們第一位
Let's first ask Guo Jiayou, the wise man, to share with us, shall we?
我們就先請郭家佑理智長來跟我們分享好嗎
Thanks
謝謝
Hello everyone, distinguished guests, friends online, hello everyone
好各位各位貴賓各位線上的朋友大家好
I am Guo Jiayou, the chairman of Taiwan Digital Diplomacy Association
我是台灣數位外交協會的理事長郭家佑
Then today's words are actually
那今天的話其實就是
I want to use some little stories from Ukraine
想用一些烏克蘭的一些小故事
Let me share with you that in the war between Ukraine and Russia
就跟大家分享一下說在烏克蘭跟俄羅斯的戰爭裡面
What are they doing for their fame?
到底他們的功名都在做些什麼事情
Because you may have seen news about Ukraine last year
因為大家可能去年的時候看到烏克蘭的新聞
There was a lot of discussion last year that
去年就有滿多的討論說
I'm an ordinary person, what kind of things can I do?
那我是一般人我到底可以做些什麼樣的事情
Because what we usually use is on social media
因為我們平常會用的就是會在社群媒體上面
I might share with you what I ate today.
可能跟大家分享今天吃了什麼啦
Or what news did you see today?
或是說今天看到什麼新聞
Is there any way for something like this to exert any influence?
那這樣子的事情到底有沒有辦法去發揮什麼影響力
We will spend 15 minutes today to briefly discuss with you
我們就是今天用15分鐘的時間跟大家簡單的討論一下
Then let me briefly introduce why our association started
那我先稍微介紹一下就是為什麼我們協會會開始
The project focuses on the defense of the network
專注在這個網路的防禦的這個計畫
First of all, it means that last year we actually
那首先就是說在去年其實我們因為過往
So the Diplomatic Council has always been on social media
所以外交協會一直都是在社群媒體上面
promoting Taiwan and other countries
在宣傳台灣跟其他國家的
partnership, so we usually hang on the Internet naturally
夥伴關係 所以我們平常其實很自然就是會掛在網路上面
It's almost like this all day to see what's happening on the Internet abroad
就幾乎就是一整天這樣子去看國外的網路發生什麼事情
Last year, we observed on the Internet that, in fact, Ukrainian
那去年的時候在網路上我們就觀察到說 其實烏克蘭的
the masses they are very
群眾他們是非常有
doing a lot spontaneously
自發性的在做很多
A lot of them will set up their own websites, information websites
很多的 他們會自己架網站 資訊網站
In other words, they will initiate some
那或者說他們會去發起一些
Some common actions on the Internet
網路上面的一些共同的行動
Then we think these things are actually worthy of Taiwan’s reference.
那我們覺得說其實這些東西都很值得台灣來做參考
Because he needs the content of these networks
因為這些網路的內容他是需要
Vision is planned or vision is
視顯被企劃 或者是視前被
Understand, it's a bit like K-Study, let's start with
了解 有點像K-Study這樣子 我們先以
Use Ukraine as a mirror, let’s see it first
烏克蘭當做借鏡 先去看說
What kind of cases have they done? In the future, when Taiwan prepares for this, compare
他們做過什麼樣子的案例 那未來台灣在做這個準備的時候比較
It won't be so busy, so
不會那麼的手忙腳亂 所以
exist
在
In the content we focus on, in fact
在我們專注的內容裡面 其實
We are not focusing on fake news
我們不是專注在假訊息
Because of false information, many units in Taiwan are actually doing it
因為假訊息其實很多台灣的單位都有在做
We are more focused on content production
我們比較專注的是在內容的產
how to go
要怎麼樣子去
After identifying fake news
假訊息辨識之後
The part behind you is going
你後面的那一段是要去
to generate from content
要去產自內容
to fight disinformation
去跟假訊息抗衡
Let's say there's probably no fake news out there.
那就算說可能沒有假訊息的存在
You also have to keep making
你也必須要持續的去製造
social content on the web
網路上面的社群內容
only you can make
你才有辦法讓
People from other countries continue to discuss
其他國家的人持續的來討論
your situation
你的處境
So today's sharing will be more focused on
所以今天的分享會比較專注在
It's what's on the internet
就是網路上面的內容
How to make it
到底要怎麼樣子來製造
good
好
Civic willfulness is this
公民任性是這個
Everyone is talking about
大家都有在討論說
what kind of action
到底什麼樣子的行動
Can be strengthened
可以強化
For example, Taiwan's Internet
比方說台灣的網路
Citizen willfulness
公民任性
To me, it's civic willfulness
對我來說其實公民任性
it's a lot of
它就是一個把很多個
A thing connected by nodes
節點連起來的一件事情
just say everyone
就在說每個人
Everyone is a channel for information dissemination
大家都是資訊傳播的管道
You have your own social platform
你有自己的社群平台
You have a network of people around you
你有自己身邊的人際網絡
everyone is one
每個人都是一個
node of information dissemination
資訊傳播的節點
Then when everyone knows how to do this
那當所有的人都知道要怎麼樣子來做這個
When information is disseminated, in fact, many of us
資訊傳播的時候呢其實我們很多的
When many dots are connected, he will become a
很多的點連起來他就會變成一個
a net
一個網
The more sticky this net is, the more self-willed citizens will be
那這個網越黏密在這個公民任性就會
stronger
越強
That
那
if we are here we can
我們在這邊的話可以
Let me share with you about last year
跟大家分享一下去年
How the Digital Diplomacy Association might be involved in this online community in Ukraine
數位外交協會可能有怎麼樣參與烏克蘭的這個網路社群
Let's say there was a meme in Ukraine last year and he was full
那比方說去年烏克蘭有一張迷因圖他還滿
The one full of red is called a headache map, that's what they say
滿紅的叫做頭痛圖就是他們說
My head hurts when I live next to Russia
住在俄羅斯的旁邊頭很痛這樣子
then we'll be
那我們馬上就是
To do one is to live in
去做了一張就是住在
China's side headache also hurts. This meme got about 230,000 likes on the Internet.
China的旁邊頭也很痛那這張迷因圖在網路上獲得大概23萬個讚
That is, everyone started to discuss the situation of Taiwan and the situation of Ukraine.
就是大家就開始來討論說那台灣的處境跟烏克蘭的處境到底
is it similar
是不是類似的
then we are
那我們在
Beyond the topic of Ukraine
烏克蘭的話題以外
In addition to the topic of Ukraine, there are actually
烏克蘭的話題以外其實也
have done some
有做過一些
did some political cartoons
有做過一些政治漫畫
We'll do political cartoons in different languages
我們會用不同的語言去做政治漫畫
For example, Lai Qingde visited Honduras before
比方說賴清德他之前出訪紅都拉斯
At that time, Hongdullas was still Taiwan's helper, but now it is not.
就那時候紅都拉斯還是台灣的幫交口現在已經不是了
In the past, when he was visiting
以前還是的時候他出訪的時候
We made him a political cartoon
我們就幫他做了一張政治漫畫
So Vice President Lai Qingde and the Vice President of the United States
所以賴清德副總統還有美國的副總統
Put it with the president of Red Durres
跟紅都拉斯的總統就放在一起
In this political cartoon they eat street food in Red Durran together
這個政治漫畫他們就在一起吃紅都拉斯的街頭小吃
So we used this political cartoon to send the first message on the Internet saying
所以我們用這個政治漫畫去網路上面傳第一個訊息說
It means being good friends with Taiwan
就是跟台灣當好朋友的話
It's like being good friends with the United States
等於就是跟美國當好朋友
This is the way to spread the word to the people of Central and South America
就是這樣子去向中南美洲的民眾做宣傳
Those private pictures
那這些民營圖
Then we'll give it back to the public in the comments
然後我們會再把它的回饋民眾的留言
will collect again
也會再收集起來
Then it will be made into international news
然後會再製作成國際新聞
It is to talk more about Taiwan's positive image abroad
就是在國外去多講一些關於台灣的正面形象的東西
that or sometimes
那或是說在有些時候
Sometimes when some countries break off diplomatic relations with Taiwan
有些時候有些國家跟台灣斷交的時候
We'll also start some
我們也會去發動一些
Actions on the Internet. For example, Solomon broke off diplomatic relations with Taiwan in 2019.
網路的行動 比方說索羅門在2019年的時候跟台灣斷交
We have initiated some
我們在索羅門的網路世界裡面有發起一些
A series of posts to talk about, although the relationship is broken
一系列的貼文去講說 雖然斷交了
But the people of Taiwan and the people of Solomon can still be good friends
可是台灣的人民跟索羅門的人民還是可以當好朋友
It also caused a lot of repercussions in the local area.
就是也在當地引起了很多的迴響這樣子
So we're doing digital diplomacy and we'll see that
那我們在做數位外交行動我們會看到說
In fact, digital diplomacy is a long-term
其實數位外交它是一個可以去透過長期的
Create community content and then influence it in other countries' societies
製造社群內容然後在其他國家的社會裡面去影響
The public opinion of the masses in other countries, or in other words, to influence the opinions of other countries
它國的群眾的輿論或者說去影響其他國家的
It is up to the people of other countries to influence the decision-making of the local government
由其他國家民眾再去影響當地政府的決策
So their digital diplomacy is actually in the current
所以他們其實數位外交它其實在現在的這個
In the online world, it is actually a relatively easy to measure
網路世界裡面其實它是一個比較容易被測量的
It has a way to measure its effectiveness and the number of people it reaches
它是有辦法去測量它的成效跟它觸及的人數的
an action like this
一種行動這樣子
So let's go back to last year, let's turn the time forward to last year
那我們回到去年我們把時間轉到去年
February 24th of last year was when Russia began its invasion of Ukraine
去年2月24日就是當俄羅斯開始入侵烏克蘭的時候
What happened to Ukraine's Internet
烏克蘭的網路發生了什麼事情
You can see that the war has not yet started, when it started to be very intense
大家可以看到戰爭還沒有開始很激烈的開始打的時候
Here we summarize a little
我們這邊稍微總結一下就是
Three days before the Ukrainian war started their
烏克蘭戰爭開打前三天他們的
Some posts by government officials on Twitter
政府官員在推特上面的一些發文
you can see that in fact
你可以看到說其實在
exist
在
72 hours into the war they say their
戰爭開打的72小時他們比方說他們的
The digital minister is a bit like their digital department
數位部長就是有點像是他們的數發部
So I started to appeal to companies all over the world
就開始跟全世界的企業去呼籲說
stop providing services to russia because they are doing illegal intrusion
不要再提供服務給俄羅斯因為他們正在進行非法的入侵
That is to say their Prime Minister will start to
那或是說他們的總理就會開始向
shout out to the world
向全世界去做喊話
then in
然後在
In these
在這些
In addition to the Ukrainian government’s own posts on the Internet, you can also see various companies
網路上面除了烏克蘭的政府自己會發文之外你也可以看到各個企業
They also tweet
他們也是透過推特
Or through Facebook or various social platforms they start responding
或是透過臉書或各種社群平台他們開始去回應
Views on the Ukraine War
對於烏克蘭戰爭的看法
So machine warfare is actually a hybrid type of warfare.
所以 機器戰爭其實是一種混合型態的戰爭
it's not just in physical wars
它不只是在實體的戰爭
This kind of mutual speech on the Internet
大家在網路上面的這種互相的發言
In fact, it will also affect the development of the entire war situation.
其實它也會去影響整個戰爭局勢的發展
Here even companies from various countries have begun to condemn Russia
在這邊就是各國的企業也開始譴責俄羅斯
Then publish it on the Internet like this
然後在網路上面去做發表這樣子
Well, Ukraine actually has a lot of government apps
那烏克蘭他們其實也有很多政府的APP
Then there are also developed
然後也有被開發出來
For example, this missing par
比方說這個缺帕
It's a shorthand in Telegram
它是在Telegram裡面的一個缺帕
It is to allow the public to go to the
它就是讓民眾可以即時的去
Repay in this Telegram trap
這個Telegram的圈套裡面去回報
A first-hand view of a situation where they are located
他們所在地的 第一手的一個狀況
This is what they digitally don't build
這個是他們的數位不打造的
Then I was in February last February
那我在二月 去年二月的時候
I have private message my Ukrainian friend
我有私訊我的烏克蘭朋友
I asked him how are you doing now?
我就問他說 你現在還好嗎
so you are now in ukraine
那你現在 你在烏克蘭
Is there anything I need help with?
有沒有什麼需要幫忙的地方
My Ukrainian friend replied
我的烏克蘭朋友就回答我說
In fact, he thinks that as long as the atrocities of Russia can be spread
其實他覺得只要可以把俄羅斯的暴行擴散出去
Letting more people know is the biggest help for them
讓更多的人知道對他們來說就是最大的幫忙
Because they actually
因為他們在這樣子的情境裡面其實
It is difficult for us to contact them directly
我們很難直接的去接觸他們
but we have internet
可是我們有網路
when we have internet
當我們有網路的時候
We can help our friends in Ukraine
我們就可以去幫助在烏克蘭的朋友
spread this information
把這樣子的資訊擴散出去
What can you do after it spreads out?
那擴散出去之後可以幹嘛
Because more and more people will discuss
因為會有越來越多人討論
will push the governments of various countries to start formalizing this issue
會去促使各國的政府開始正式這個議題
The governments of various countries will impose sanctions on Russia
各國政府才會去對俄羅斯進行一個制裁
the community actually
那社群其實
The community as a small brother's big combat tool
社群作為一小伯大的作戰工具
Then we will share with you today
那在我們的今天也跟大家分享一下
In other words, it is used by communities between Taiwan and Ukraine
說就是臺灣跟烏克蘭中間的社群的使用
What is the difference between us
到底我們到底差異在哪裡
or did something different
或是做了什麼樣子不一樣的事情
good
好
the whole world
那全世界
What the whole world does with the community is actually what he basically wants
全世界用社群做的事情 其實他基本上就是要
Do your best to help Ukraine spread the message
盡力的協助烏克蘭來做訊息的傳播
Because in war, there is one very important thing
因為在打仗的時候 有一件很重要的事情
is to build a value alliance
就是要建立一個價值的同盟
Then you have to go to all the Internet to discuss this matter
那你要去把所有網路上面 在討論這件事情
pull to the same side as you feel saying
拉到跟你同一邊 覺得說
He agrees with you in this war
他同意你在這場戰爭裡面的
legitimacy and morality, so the community can spread
正當性跟道德性 所以社群他是一個可以去散播
your values ​​spread your values ​​and go
你的價值觀 傳播你的價值觀 還有去
A platform to influence public opinion
影響群眾意見的一個平台
For example, the previous icon has to be
那比方說之前的icon有要把
The domain of the former Soviet Union was removed, and this is also in
前蘇聯的網域拿掉 這個也是在
One made after some discussions on the Internet
網路上面的一些討論之後做出的一個
A decision looks like this or in
一個決策這樣子 那或是說在
There are many politicians in Ukraine and they will go
烏克蘭有很多的政治人物 他們會去
will go for a specific specific event to happen
會去針對特定的 特定的事件做發生
You can see that in these
你可以看到說在這些
That is, in the speeches of politicians, they are actually targeting
就是政治人物的發言裡面 他們其實都是在針對
They are actually targeting that, that is what international organizations are doing.
他們其實都是在針對那個就是國際組織在做
International organizations are making a call
國際組織在做一個呼籲
can help me next page thanks
可以幫我下一頁謝謝
So here’s what you can say to him on social media
那這邊的話就是或是說在社群媒體上面可以跟他說
For example, if there are people from Ukraine, they will contact Beckham
比方說有烏克蘭的民眾他們就會去聯絡貝克罕
Then they borrowed Beckham's IG
那他們借了貝克罕的IG
Then convey the battle situation in the Ukrainian hospital
然後把烏克蘭醫院裡面的戰況就是轉達出去
Because Beckham has a lot of traffic
因為貝克罕的流量非常的多
It is said that this post has been seen by 4 million people
這個動態聽說有400萬個人看到
So they use different social platforms
所以他們會利用不同的社群平台
Or to work with different hospital leaders
或是說去跟不同的醫院領袖合作
Then go to convey the content they have done and find the right channel to spread it out
然後去轉達把他們做好的內容找到正確的管道傳播出去
ok help me next page thanks
好幫我下一頁謝謝
So what did Ukraine do with the community?
那烏克蘭用社群又做了哪些事情呢
In fact, they are mainly in Ukraine to maintain the popularity of a community
其實烏克蘭他們就是主要是在維持一個社群的熱度
Because their worst fear is that the world won't talk about them
因為他們最害怕的事情就是全世界不討論他們
when they are not discussed
當他們沒有被討論的時候
They are a state of isolation
他們就是一個孤立無遠的狀態
So Ukrainians use community
所以烏克蘭人他們用社群
The main thing they do is
他們最主要做的事情就是
To maintain the enthusiasm of a community
去維持一個社群的熱度
can you help me with the next one thanks
可以再幫我下一個嗎 謝謝
Then their posts are actually
那他們的貼文其實
You can see that they actually have
可以去看到說他們其實有
Whether it's an emotional post
不管是比較情緒性的貼文
or more informative posts
或者比較資訊性的貼文
In fact, their request for publication will
其實他們的發文的訴求會
The request for posting will be different
發文的訴求會不太一樣
sometimes they do memes
有些時候他們會做迷因圖
Will make meme maps or will make some
會做迷因圖或是會去做一些
Comparison of photos before and after the war
戰爭前 戰爭後的照片的比較
that is a more emotional
那就是一個比較情緒性
It's a way of posting to arouse public awareness
就是引發公感的一種貼文的方式
can help me next page
可以再幫我下一頁
There are more informational posts
那資訊性的貼文的話就比較多是
For example, the government will issue an announcement saying
比方說政府會去發佈說
What are the methods of disinformation commonly used in Russia?
俄羅斯常用的假訊息的手法有哪些
Or where is the current supply spreading?
或是說現在的供給又擴散到哪邊了
So there are some more informative posts
所以也有些比較資訊性的貼文
In the communication of the community, it doesn’t matter whether it is
那在社群的傳播裡面其實不管是
informational or emotional hearing
是資訊性還是情緒性的聽聞
Both are needed
這兩種都是需要的
ok help me next page
好可以再幫我下一頁
Then I actually think that the Ukrainian government or the masses
然後其實我覺得烏克蘭的政府或群眾
They know how to express their needs through the community
他們都很懂得怎麼透過社群去表達自己的需求
Because you have to express your needs before you know how to say
因為要表達需求你才會知道說
That is, the foreign government or the masses abroad
就是到底國外的國外的政府或國外的群眾
how to help
要怎麼樣子來做幫忙
can help me next page
可以再幫我下一頁
And then to the one who just said that they're actually pretty good at going
然後對剛剛有講到說他們其實很擅長去
They are very good at cooperating with some overseas opinion leaders
跟他們很擅長去跟海外的一些意見領袖做合作
For example Stephen King made a post for them
比方說史蒂芬金就幫他們發了一篇貼文
This traffic is very high
這個流量就非常的高
ok help me next page
好再幫忙下一頁
to that
對那
I just mentioned that the masses in Ukraine are very good at expressing their needs
剛剛講到說烏克蘭的群眾他們很會表達自己的需求
Let's say there is a website called supportUkrain
那比方說有一個網站叫做supportUkrain
This website is actually open to foreigners
這個網站它其實是開給外國人看的
It's open to foreigners who want to support Ukraine
它開給想要支持烏克蘭的外國人看
It tells you that in fact you have a lot of ways
它告訴你說其實你有非常多的方法
Can go to help people in Ukraine no matter what
可以去幫助烏克蘭的人不管是提供
Say asylum or say you want to donate
避難說 或者說你要捐款
Or you're going to be a volunteer and you're going to help them do translations
或者說你要成為志工 你要幫忙他們做翻譯
or you want his
或是你要把他的
That is, you have to provide all kinds of organizational contacts, and he integrates all of them into
就是你要提供各式各樣的組織聯絡 他把他全部整合在
All in one website
一個 全部整合在一個網站裡面
That
那
He even said he would
他甚至說會把
different
不同的
post he will too
貼文 他也是會
Put him all together, that is, his actions on the Internet, he also integrates him
把他全部 就是把他網路上面的行動 他也把他整合起來
Before that, you may have heard that the Ukrainian people proposed to go to
那之前可能大家有聽過說烏克蘭民眾他們有發起說要去
Under the Google Map of Russia
俄羅斯的Google Map底下
Go leave a comment because the people of Russia didn't know their country was at war when they first attended
去留言 因為過俄羅斯的民眾一開始出席的時候他們並不知道自己國家正在打仗
so
所以
at that time
那時候
Villagers in Ukraine launched a gambling operation called Go
烏克蘭的鄉民有發起博行動叫做去
Google Map of Russia
俄羅斯的Google Map
This left a message today, so he also put this online action on this website, which means saying
這個今天底下留言 所以他也把這個網路行動也有放在這個網站裡面等於說
You just go to this site and you can
你只要到這個網站你就可以
click into various
點進去各種
Participate in some actions on the Internet
網路上面的一些行動去做參與
very convenient
非常的方便
ok help me next page
好 再幫我下一頁
Then in this case, we are still talking about Telegram
然後在這個的話就還是在講Telegram
That is, everyone can see that Telegram is in the war between black and evil
就是大家可以看到說Telegram在烏惡戰爭裡面
actually played a very important role
其實扮演了蠻重要的角色
Because in the war between black and evil, there are actually Telegram groups
因為在烏惡戰爭裡面其實Telegram的群組
He's growing at about the same rate as before.
他成長的速度是大概是以往的
Six times as much as when there was no war
沒有戰爭的時候的六倍
He has new groups every day
他每天都會有新的群組
to provide new information
因為要提供新的資訊
would say he would have a different newsgroup
會說他會有不同的新聞群組
I can exchange messages with you
可以去跟大家交換訊息
There are also many foreigners
那也有很多的外國群眾
They participate in these Telegrams
他們參與在這些Telegram裡面去
To provide assistance or to get first-hand information
提供協助或是說去得到第一手的資訊
In fact, the most important thing for us to do online content is to
其實我們做網路內容最重要就是要
to create or to find new pipelines
去創造或去找到新的管道
Bring the news that is originally in the country to the foreign country
把本來在國內的消息帶到國外去
ok help me next page
好 再幫我下一頁
So what did the Taiwanese use the community to do?
那台灣人用社群又做了哪些事情
The Taiwanese actually did quite a lot
那台灣人其實做了蠻多
Just last year, I actually did quite a lot of interesting things
就在去年的時候其實有做了蠻多有趣的東西
can help me next page
可以幫我下一頁
Let's say we are the presidential palace
就比方說我們就是總統府
There is a Ukrainian blue flower
有發一個烏克蘭的藍花
is to express a profound support for Ukraine
就是表達一個對烏克蘭的深遠支持
then on the next page thanks
然後在下一頁 謝謝
Before our association made a picture called
我們協會之前有做一張圖片叫做
That is, Taiwan stands with Ukraine
就是Taiwan stands with Ukraine
This is a picture of black bear and white he
這一個黑熊白賀圖
Black bear represents Taiwan and Bai He represents Ukraine
黑熊是代表台灣 白賀是代表烏克蘭
Then we call on netizens to post this picture on various
那我們就是號召網友去把這張圖片貼在各個
Posted under the tweets of various Ukrainian politicians
貼在各個烏克蘭政治人物的推特底下
Just leave a message to express an emotional support
去做留言就表達一個情感上的支持
Then this picture has more than 4,000 netizens who came to like it
那這張圖片大概4000多個網友有來按讚
is that we take a network action to express
就是我們採取一個網路的行動表達
So Taiwan stands with Ukraine
所以台灣是跟烏克蘭站在一起的
can help me next page thanks
可以再幫我下一頁 謝謝
Then we also observed that
那我們那時候也觀察到說
In fact, Taiwanese netizens are very concerned about Ukraine
其實台灣的網友非常的關注烏克蘭
Let's say in the first week of the war
比方說在戰爭發生的第一個禮拜
One of our Ukrainian friends sent us a photo
我們的一個烏克蘭朋友他就寄了一張照片給我們
He is a blogger who has been to Taiwan
他是一個來過台灣的部落客
He just likes it and says I'm still safe in Ukraine
他就只是比個讚 然後說我在烏克蘭我仍很安全
At that time, there were probably more than a thousand Taiwanese netizens who liked it
那時候大概就有一千多個台灣網友來按讚
In fact, this network has
其實這個網路有
The interesting thing is that even though you don't know him at all and you haven't met him
有趣的地方就是說 雖然你跟他是完全不認識也沒有見過面
But because out of a humanitarian concern that everyone is human
可是因為出於一個 就是大家都是人的一個人道關懷
So you'll be safe as long as you see there are Ukrainians
所以你只要看到有烏克蘭人是平安的
In fact, you will create a link with him through this posting net.
其實你就會透過這個貼網安占去跟他產生一個連結
can help me next page
可以再幫我下一頁
That's right, we're actually helping too.
那對 就是我們其實也有在協助
Our association also often assists the Ukrainian community in Taiwan to forward some news
我們協會也常常在協助在台灣的烏克蘭社群去轉發一些消息
Because they want to raise funds with the general public in Taiwan
因為他們想要跟不管是跟台灣社會大眾募款
Or call on the people to take to the streets to support
或是號召民眾上街頭去支援
To support Ukraine, this is our association to help forward a message
支援烏克蘭這個就是我們協會去幫忙做一個訊息的轉發
can help me next page
可以再幫我下一頁
Then in the NFT part, there are actually a lot of creative activities on the Internet
然後在NFT的部分其實網路上也有很多的創作行動
It's a fundraiser for Ukraine.
是在幫烏克蘭做募款
Fundraising for Ukraine
在幫烏克蘭做募款
Even though the amount last year was not very high
就是去年的金額雖然沒有到很高
But I think that is a new attempt by the Taiwanese community
可是我覺得那個是台灣社群一個新的嘗試
As far as NFT can be used for a charity-related fundraising operation
就NFT居然是可以拿來做一個慈善相關的募款行動
there are many people
那有很多人
willing to participate
願意來做參與
ok help me next page
好幫我下一頁
In these matters, Ukraine gave Taiwan
那在這些事情裡面烏克蘭給台灣
what a revelation
什麼樣子的啟示
Revelation, in fact, we can see that
啟示呢其實我們可以看到說
Everyone in Ukraine
在烏克蘭真裡面大家
The most important thing is to find a channel to spread the message
最重要的就是要找到傳播訊息的管道
Those things he he is not
那這些東西他他不是
When something happens, you go find it
遇到事情的時候你再去找
It’s fine, he’s normal, so he needs to get ready slowly.
就就可以他是一些平常就要慢慢準備起來
Or writing content or doing dissemination
或是說寫內容或是說做傳播
This kind of work also needs
這樣子的工作那也是要
through daily practice
透過每天每天的練習
And to think about these themes
還有去發想這些主題
That needs to be prepared in advance.
那個都是需要先提前做準備的
So we talk about transition from peace to war
所以我們講平戰轉換
Normal and temporary conversion
平時跟暫時的轉換
ok help me next page
好再幫我下一頁
we are in this year
我們在在今年在
Taiwan has done one
台灣有做過一個
The group screen project of Taiwan Community Guardian
台灣社群守衛者的群幕計畫
then we just want to say
那我們就是希望說
can come to upgrade
可以來提升
Taiwan's Cyber ​​Operations Propagation Capabilities
台灣的網路作戰的傳播能力
then we are not fake news
那我們不是做假訊息
Because fake news is really a lot of people doing it
因為假訊息真的非常多人在做
in our opinion
就我們覺得說
A small piece of Taiwan is what is needed
台灣有一小塊就是是需要
Let's discuss what we are going to do in this special war period
來討論說我們到底要怎麼樣子在特殊的戰爭時期
Know how to do this kind of communication work
懂得來做這種傳播的工作
In this dissemination work, whether it is to make a report on domestic information
在這個傳播工作裡面不管是對國內把資訊做一個
Integrate, or in other words, foreign countries, is to make Taiwan's situation external
整合或是說對國外就是要把台灣的狀況往外
Communication maintains a degree of discussion throughout the international community
傳播保持一個整個國際社會的一個討論度
These need to be cultivated slowly
這些都是需要慢慢培養的
So we have a plan to launch a group screen this year
所以我們在今年有推出一個群幕的計畫
can help me next page
可以再幫我下一頁
The group screen project is very grateful to more than 400 donors this year
群幕的計畫在今年就是很感謝有400多個捐款人
There is a plan to support this
就是有支持這樣子的計畫
So we are doing a series of courses this year
所以我們今年在做一個系列的課程
can help me next page
可以再幫我下一頁
We have a series of courses this year
我們在今年有做一個系列的課程
That is for friends in different professional fields
那是針對不同的專業領域的朋友
So let's go and create communication courses that belong to different professional fields.
那我們去開設屬於不同專業領域的傳播課程
Then we are also developing a set of card games at the same time
那我們同時也有在開發一套牌卡遊戲
Well, this card game is actually for everyone to play different roles.
那這個牌卡遊戲其實它就是讓大家去扮演不同的
Role
角色
like when a war breaks out
就比方說戰爭發生的時候
If you are usually a marketing communication person
如果你平常是一個做行銷傳播的人員
you are usually an engineer
你平常是一個工程師
or you are usually a teacher
或是你平常是一個老師
you are in such a situation
你在這樣的情境裡面
what can everyone do
大家各自可以做什麼樣的事情
For example, if you are usually a teacher
那比方說你平常是一個老師的話
You may have to teach teachers in our courses
你可能我們的課程裡面有去教老師
In the final analysis, how to improve students
說到底要怎麼樣子去提升學生
Ability to make media attempts or information interpretation
做媒體試圖或是資訊判讀的能力
There are actually different characters in this card game
在這套牌卡遊戲裡面其實有不同的角色
For example, there is another character called Overseas Taiwanese
比方說還有一個角色叫做海外台灣人
The role of overseas Taiwanese
海外台灣人的角色
We will teach you in the course
我們就是會在課程裡面去教大家
Say if you are a study abroad student today
說如果你今天是一個在海外留學
or Taiwanese working overseas
或是在海外工作的台灣人
How do you contact the local government media
你要怎麼樣子來聯絡當地的政府媒體
Or to help with a translation job
或是說來幫忙做一個翻譯的工作
So everyone can play in this card game
所以大家可以在這套牌卡遊戲
or in our online courses
或是我們的線上課程裡面
You can find different positions that may belong to you
可以找到不同的可能屬於自己的定位
or role
或是角色
to do simulations to make predictions
來做模擬來做預言
To rehearse the communication operations on the Internet in advance
事前的去演練這些網路上面的傳播作戰
How to proceed like this
到底要這麼進行
OK, you can help me on the next page
好 可以再幫我下一頁
that this is the last page
那這邊是最後一頁
It's the conclusion, simply put
就是結論簡單來說就是說
Cognitive warfare is actually a
認知作戰其實是一個
Topics that cannot be ignored in Taiwan
台灣不可以去忽視的話題
It happens in our daily life
它發生在我們每一天的日常生活當中
Our daily life is
我們每一天的日常生活都是
need to identify information
需要去辨識資訊
In addition to identifying information
那除了辨識資訊以外
Become a Disseminator of Information
自己成為資訊的傳播者
and being able to produce content from people
還有成為有能力去產自內容的人
This is one of the ways to raise the awareness of Taiwanese citizens
這個就是提升台灣公民認識的其中一種方法
That's what I want to share with you the most today
那就是今天最想跟大家分享的事情
ok help me last page
好 再幫我最後一頁
If you are online
那如果各位在網上
If you are interested, you can go to our fan page
各位有興趣的話就是可以上我們的粉專
You can go to our fan special
就是可以上我們的粉專
is to refer to the digital diplomacy action plan
就是參考數位外交行動計畫
Then our IG and Twitter are both DG Diplo Lab
然後我們的IG跟Twitter都是DG Diplo Lab
That or you have more questions
那或是大家有更多的疑問
or have something to discuss
或是有想要討論的話題
You can remember our Email
都可以記到我們的Email
probably over here thanks
大概就到這邊 謝謝
Then we are very grateful to Chairman Guo for his sharing just now.
那我們非常謝謝郭理事長剛剛的分享
I think the game just now was just the board game
我覺得其實剛剛的遊戲剛剛那個桌遊
I just remind you that there is a design
我就提醒到一點 就是有設計上
There seem to be many characters
好像有很多的角色嘛
That actually represents different people in our society.
那其實是代表我們社會上不同的人
Then each of us might want to say
那我們每個人可能都會想說
It seems that the war is far away from me
好像戰爭離我很遠
or a real war
或真的發生戰爭的
I can't seem to do it when
我好像什麼時候不能做
But I think this reminder just now is the discovery
但我覺得這張剛剛的提醒就是發現
Not really
不盡然
everyone at their job
每個人在自己的工作崗位上
One of your usual professional abilities
你自己平時的一個專業能力
both may be available in time of war
都可能可以在戰爭的時候
let's play some roles
讓我們扮演一些角色
Let's be able to have some of this for the defense of Taiwan
讓我們能夠有一些這個對防衛台灣
helpful place
有助的地方
That just mentioned a lot of points
那剛剛有提到很多一個點
Talking Screen Battle Transformation
講說屏戰轉換
sometimes what is needed in wartime
有時候戰時所需要的東西
It may be necessary to prepare in advance
在平時可能就要事先做好準備
Maybe it's not a wartime application
也許平時不是在做戰時的應用
But you have to put this function first
但是必須先把這個功能
some infrastructure to design
一些基礎建設給設計好
so i think next
所以我覺得接下來
also the next speaker
也是下一位講者
In fact, this is a very important reason
其實是這個非常重要的原因
The previous Guo Dizhang mentioned
前面那個郭底帳提到
Ukraine seems to be making an App
烏克蘭好像做一個App
so that they can temporarily
讓他們可以在暫時的時候
Like can do something like identify the position of the enemy
像可以什麼譬如辨識敵軍的位置
Or let ordinary people know some situations
或讓一般的人如果知道一些狀況
You can use that App to repay
可以用那個App去回報
As far as Taiwan is concerned, as far as we know
那台灣我們就我們目前所知
Seems like the government doesn't have one like this
好像政府沒有一個像這樣子
A digital tool that can be used by everyone
一個可以給大家使用的一個數位工具使用
It doesn't matter if the government doesn't do it
政府不做沒關係
The great thing about Taiwan is that
我們台灣的厲害的地方就是
Our masters are among the people
我們高手在民間
Folks can do it
民間可以有人來做
I think this is just wait a minute we're going to ask for this
我想這個就是等一下我們要請這個
The place dad wants to share with us
哈爸要跟我們分享的地方
What kind of way did he use to let us Taiwan
他用什麼樣的方式然後讓我們台灣
own folk have a tool
自己的民間有一個工具
can be a digital tool
可以去做一個數位工具
come and do a potential
來去做一種潛在
Maybe for now we can take one of the apps
也許暫時我們可以拿應用的一個
Effectively identify the enemy or this
有效辨識敵人啊或是這個
The method of group combat comes to us next please
團體作戰的方法來我們接下來請
Thank you Dad
我們哈爸謝謝
so everyone can do
所以大家都能做的
I will use my left palm
那我用左掌來
try it first
先試一下
wow, there's a nice screen on the front
哇 前面還有一個漂亮的螢幕
Hello everyone, I am Abba
大家好 我是阿爸
The front side, eh, the header video won’t come out
前面這邊 欸 它頭影片不會出來
That's okay, I'll just watch it
那是沒關係 那我就用看的
what did you think
那你剛才是怎麼看
It doesn't matter
沒關係
oh yes
喔對齁
eh yes
欸 有啦
good
好
then i will start
那我就開始了
Hello everyone, I am Abba
大家好 我是阿爸
Saints call me Abba
聖女都叫我阿爸
My real name is Xu Wulong
我本名叫徐武龍
Then the first page of this head video
那這個頭影片的第一頁
Its upper left corner is C700NAM
它的左上角就是C700NAM
It means that this file is public
就表示這個文件它是公開的
so if given the chance
所以有機會的話
Then please host this header video
再請主辦就把這個頭影片
can share with everyone
可以分享給大家
The QR code in the lower right corner is
右下角那個QR code就是
All relevant information scan this QR code
所有相關的資料 掃這個QR code
Just put it in your mouth and there will be
就要口進去就會有
ok then let's start
好 那我們就開始吧
Okay, I'm going to start off by sharing a little bit
好 我一開始我想先稍微分享一下
some fumbling agendas of my own
自己的一些摸索的議程
I think
我覺得
From these years we know
從這幾年我們知道
Three needles have a chance
三針有機會來
To be honest, I was very worried at first.
其實老實講一開始是非常擔心的
The more you worry the more you want to know
你越擔心你就越希望去了解
The more you understand, the more you worry
越了解其實你就更擔心
but you keep watching
可是你一直看
like my own case is
像我自己的情況是
you're worried you'll want to see what's going on
你擔心你就會去想要看什麼情況
What is the status of the input
辨識輸到的狀況是什麼
To put it simply, for example, should we flee or should we defend?
簡單講 比方說該逃還是該守
This is the basic question
這是基本要想的問題
I can't bear it, so I should run away, right?
撐不住是不是要該逃了對不對
But when you get to know more
可是你當你越去了解
Like I just said, I get to know more
像剛剛講 越去了解
In fact, besides worrying
其實你除了擔心以外
In fact, you will find that there is really very little you can do
其實你會發現你能做的真的非常少
Because each of these things seems to be a big thing
因為這東西每一個都好像是很大的事情
It's like the president or something
好像都是總統什麼什麼
to be able to handle things that the government can handle
才能夠處理政府才能處理的事情
what does that have to do with us
那跟我們什麼關係
but you slowly find
但是你慢慢發現
You will watch for a long time and you will find out that
你會看月久之後你就會發現說
In fact, this can't work.
其實這樣不行啊
what's the use of worrying
你只有擔心有什麼用
most importantly
最重要是
my idea is this
我的想法是這樣
don't worry if you want
你要嘛就不要擔心
So if you're worried then you have to do something
那你如果擔心那你就要做點什麼
So I'm here to appeal to you by the way
所以我在這裡就是順便跟大家呼籲一下
the importance of action
行動的重要
must take action
一定要有行動
whatever you do whatever
不管你做什麼 whatever
you just start doing it
你只要開始去做
naturally less worry
自然就比較不會擔心
That's what I think
那這個是我覺得
In the process of groping
摸索過程裡面
first thing is this
第一件事是這個
You have to find a way and take action
你要想辦法要有行動
But the first problem you will encounter is
可是你會遇到第一個問題就是
You really don't know what you can do
其實你還真不知道你能做什麼行動
You say like we engage in community
你說像我們搞社群的
You said I can for war something
你說我可以 for war 什麼東西
Yes, but the war is not here yet
對啊 可是戰爭又還沒來
What are you going for war for?
你要 for war 什麼對不對
what do you want to notify
你要通知什麼
Then take a long time to learn
那當學慢慢久
second thing i found
第二件事我發現
In fact, you only need the second thing
其實你光第二件事
It's about finding a partner
是找同伴聯繫相關
Intentional organization works well
有心的組織效果很好
In fact, I have only entered this process.
這個其實已經光我進到這個進程
it's been a long time
它已經是很久以後的事
That is to say, it took you a long time to find out
就是說你搞了很久才發現
In fact, the most important thing for you is
其實你最重要的就是
just to find those friends
就是要去找到那些朋友
or someone with a heart
或者有心的人
you will feel very strange
你會覺得很奇怪
There seems to be worried person
好像擔心的人好像有
but you don't know who he is
但是你又不知道他是誰
Okay, so actually let's say later go to the black bear
好 那實際上比方說後來去參加黑熊
you will find
你就會發現
In fact, many caring people
其實很多有心的人
a lot of people with a lot of heart doing a lot of things
很多有心的人在做很多事情
but you yourself behind the screen
但是你自己在螢幕後面
or how
或者怎麼樣
In fact, it is not easy for you to find out
其實你不容易發現
but you just get out
但是你只要走出來
went to an event or two
去參加過一兩次活動
you will find
你就會發現
In fact, there are many people who are very close to you
其實跟你很接近的人很多
And everyone is doing a little bit of everything
而且大家多少什麼都在做一點
and when you find out
而且當你發現
when you start doing something
你開始做一點什麼的時候
your friends
你的這些夥伴
he will appear very strange
他都會出現很奇怪
like these today
像今天來這些
many do not know
很多就不知道
Why have we been in touch before?
為什麼以前也是都有聯繫
that's it
就是這樣子
that he is not alone
就是他不孤單
It's just that everyone compares
只是大家都比較
That is, the Low profile is relatively indifferent
就是Low profile比較不講
So the second thing is
所以第二件事情就是
you like me my basic advice
你像我我的最基本建議
is that you may say black bear
就是你可能比方說黑熊
or other activities of private houses
或者其他那些什麼民房的活動
you just try to participate
你只要試著去參加
you will find
你就會發現
this pipe will be fine
這個管道就會很好
and most importantly
而且最重要
The most important thing is to say that we speak from a personal perspective
最重要是說 我們就以個人的角度來講
when war really happens
真的發生戰事的時候
you really need friends
你其實就是需要朋友
just need pipes
就是需要管道
just need information
就是需要資訊
just need these things
就是需要這些東西
But you usually know these people
可是你平常有認識這些人
or have access to these organizations
或者有接近這些組織
What you get is the best and most first-hand information
你得到的都是最好 最一手的資料
So this usually has to be cultivated
所以這個平常是要耕耘的
Actually the last thing
其實最後就是一件事情
It means you have to play your part
就是說你要發揮自己一份戰力
that is
就是說
20 million people, you have 20 million copies for 20 million people
兩千萬人 你兩千萬人有兩千萬份
You don't have to think too much about what the government should do
你不用想那麼多 什麼政府該做什麼
Actually, I think that thing is for me
其實我覺得那個東西對我自己來講
Instead of telling people who to do
你與其一直叫人家誰該做什麼
what should you do what organization do what government do
你該做什麼組織 該做什麼政府 該做什麼
why don't you think about what you should do
你怎麼不去想想你自己該做什麼
You protect yourself, these are the most basic
你自己保護好自己這些都是最基本的
So it's important that you do your part
所以重要的就是你要發揮自己一份力量
what is that strength
那一份力量是什麼
You have to define yourself to find
你要自己去定義自己去找
like i say
像我的話就是說
Find the angle that suits you best
找最適合自己的角度 角度切入
Is my information strong?
像我資訊比較強嗎
Then of course I will start from the information
那我當然就從資訊來切入
you like me going to black bears
你像我去參加黑熊
he has ambulance
他有的是救護的
I'm not good at first aid, am I?
我又不會 不太會救護對不對
You asked me to move people, I don’t want to move others, it’s fine
你叫我搬人 我自己不要給人家搬就不錯了
Yes, that's why you will find it strange
對 就是 所以你會發現 奇怪啊
I have been engaged in information for so long, so of course it is not very good for me to come out and play a role like an information soldier
我資訊搞這麼久 那我當然出來當類似當資訊兵的角色不是很好
So the information warfare aspect is something I can ponder.
所以資訊戰的方面就是我可以琢磨的
So my goal this year is to teach Black Bear all the information warfare courses.
所以我今年我的目標呢 就是去把黑熊的那些什麼資訊戰的課都把他上完
Right, then there may be more professional scholars
對不對 那可能就有更多的本職學人
means find something you can do
就是說找一些自己能做的事情
I just want to let everyone know
那我只是先讓大家知道說
In fact, the process should be very similar for everyone.
其實大家應該進程都很像啦
Then this is an introduction I gave you at the beginning, it is my own exploration experience
那這就是一個我一開始給大家的引言 就是自己摸索的經歷
Alright, today's topic is some flexible use of Atec's digital willfulness
好 那今天的主題是Atec該數位任性的一些活用
Well, first of all, let me tell you, please play the video for me, okay?
那首先一開始先跟大家講 幫我播一下影片好不好
First let me show you what is called Atec
先給大家看一下什麼叫做Atec
Okay, this is a wait, it's an Atec one
好 這個是等一下播放的是Atec的一個
his demo video
他的展示影片
he is an american
他是一個美國
A combat software used by American soldiers
美國大兵用的一個戰鬥軟體
This is so clear
這個這樣看得看清楚
You can see he's used by GIs
你可以看到他是美國大兵在用的
But actually we can also use
但實際上我們也可以用到
Then he is very powerful
然後他這個東西很厲害
Yes, he is already an actual combat base
是他已經是實戰base
You see he is battle proven
你看他是battle proven
That is to say, he is the actual combat base
就是說他是實戰base
he is available
他是可用的
Not just toys or just games
不是只是玩具或者只是遊戲
He's something that can really be used in battle
他是真正可以拿來戰鬥使用的東西
Simply put, this is one of the American soldiers.
那簡單講這是美國大兵的一個
combat software
戰鬥軟體
You can see he has a base map
你可以看到他有底圖
You can switch between various basemaps
各式各樣的底圖你都可以切換
you can see he can know
你可以看到他可以知道
This is 3D
這個是3D
He can see 3D on his screen
他可以在他的畫面上看到3D
Each team can be seen on the map
每一隊的人都可以在地圖上看到
Can measure distance
可以測量距離
This is the position of each team
這個是每一隊的位置
then this is the weather
然後這個是天氣
he can
他可以
Incorporate current weather information
結合現在的天氣資訊
then this is
然後這個是
this is
這個是
Don't be like a camera or a drone's image
不要像camera或者是無人機的影像
will directly see
會直接看得到
So this is what it looks like when a lot of people are moving
那這個是當一大多人在動的時候的樣子
This is actually used in combat
這個是真的在戰鬥時候在用的
He has a lot of combinations
他這個結合非常多的
hardware
的硬體
You can see that there are a lot of icones here
你可以看到這裡有非常多的icone
Then he is the standard interface of the US military
然後他是美軍標準的界面
so everyone you see
所以你每個人看到的
will have the same meaning
的理解上的意思都會是一樣的
Here is the comparison of all high-level
這裡比較是所有的高層
After you are blocked by three in a certain position
跟你在某一個位置被三擋住之後
what else can you see
你還看得到什麼
Well, this is a bit like task assignment.
那這個是有點像任務分配的
the location of everyone in
的每一個人的位置
or the angle of a certain war zone
或者某一個戰區的角度
This is all the points, every running line, all the information on the line is available
這就是所有的點,每一個跑的在線上,線上所有的資訊都有
Communication interface, he can communicate with other people at any time
通訊介面,他可以隨時跟其他人做溝通
This is a drama, because he is a combat software, so you need to know where others are, where they are, and where they are defending
這個是策劇,因為他是戰鬥軟體嘛,所以要知道別人在哪裡,位置在哪,防衛在哪
This is from a drone, what the drone sees
這個是無人機的,無人機看到的樣子
ok no more
好了 沒有了
Okay, the software I just looked at
好 這個剛才看的那個軟體
Of course it's very cool, the video statement just now
當然很炫的 剛才那個影言
Tell me this sounds like I developed it
跟我說 這個好像聽起來讓我開發的
Don't get this wrong, it was developed by the US military
千萬不要這個搞錯 這個美軍開發的
related to us
跟我們有關係
Well, actually, I think we should talk about this
好 那其實我覺得講這個東西
Its first thing is that just what does it matter to me
它的第一件就是那剛我什麼關係
I can't use anything from the US military.
那美軍的東西我也用不到
Then what shall I say today?
那我今天來怎麼講
What does digital humanity have to do with me?
數位人性這跟我有什麼關係
Only when there is a relationship
有關係才要講
ok this start
好 這個一開始
What was that 3.6 Pro just now?
剛才那個什麼3.6 Pro
That's the video just now
那個就是剛才的影片
Simply put it is
簡單講它是
GI Live Combat Software
美國大兵的現場戰鬥軟體
Stable and safe through the field test
穩定安全經的起現場考驗
Suitable for battle crystals
適合戰鬥群晶
Everything about it is U.S. military standard
它所有東西都是美軍標準
ok what does that have to do with us
好 那跟我們有什麼關係
first thing
第一件事情呢
it is actually
它實際上是
like open source
像是open source的
If you have an Android phone, you can
你可以在 你如果你有Android手機
You can go directly to download and install
你可以直接下去下載安裝
So you just wait and install it straight away
所以你等一下就可以直接把它安裝完了
That
那
That's because it's open source and free
那因為它是開源的 又是免費的
So those things you just saw
所以你剛才看到的那些東西
Actually eighty to ninety percent
實際上百分之八九十
You're on your own Android phone and you're ready to go
你在你自己的Android手機 馬上就可以用了
so i'm not telling you a
所以我不是在跟你講一個
an advanced thing far away no
遠在天邊的一個高級東西 沒有
I'm talking to you about something you can use on your phone in ten minutes
我跟你講的是你十分鐘後就可以在你手機上用的東西
and it's free
而且是免費的
ok what else does it have
好 那它還有什麼
It has wind tag and itag so you iOS
它有wind tag 和itag 所以你iOS
In fact, Windows can also be used, but it is not recommended
Windows其實也可以用 但其實都不太建議
Basically you use the Android
基本上你就是在Android上用
good that
好 那
then you can imagine it that thing
那你就可以想像它那個東西
if not in combat
如果不在戰鬥的時候用
What can it be used for? You can think about it
可以拿來做什麼用 那你可以想
Things that can be used in battle are actually disaster prevention
戰鬥上可以用的東西 其實在防災
Disaster relief, mountaineering, task force, stuff like that
救災 登山 任務小組這些東西
In fact, they are very similar, the situation is very similar
其實它都很像 情境都很像
So actually you can use
所以其實都可以用
then if we are really
那如果我們真的在
When fighting happens, for example
在戰鬥發生的時候 比如說
Here are a few examples. For example, you
這裡就幾個例子 比如說你
well for example
好 比如說
where is the supply where is the water
哪裡有補給 水在哪裡
Well, for example, where is the well and where can I get it?
好 那比如說井在哪裡 哪裡取得到
get something then if you are
取得到東西 那你如果是
If you walk outside, where is your partner?
走在外面的話 你的夥伴在哪裡
For example, suppose you have
你比如說 假設現在有
there is that
有那個 有
Air defense or something
有防空啊 或者什麼
For example, you are now in disaster
比如說 你現在災害 你
Let's say you have a place where there's a bomb shelter
比如說 你有一個地方 有一個防空洞
Or an evacuation facility, but that's not the point
或者是避難設施 可是重點不在於
where is it the point is that it's inside now
它在哪裡 重點在於 它現在裡面
Is there anything else?
還有沒有 就是
Is there still room, is there enough water in it?
還有沒有空間 裡面有沒有足夠的水
Is there something so your information
有沒有什麼東西 所以你這些資訊
needs to be updated, then we are
是需要更新的 那我們在
These things in our current system are very weak
我們現在的系統裡面 這些東西它都非常弱
But it is very easy for you to use this software
但是你透過這個軟體卻非常容易
That's where this software comes in handy
那這就是這個軟體很好用的地方
Then it's written here, since it's combat software
那這裡寫的 既然它是戰鬥軟體
So of course it can happen during combat
所以在戰鬥的時候 當然可以發生
great use
很大的用途
For example, it is more useful for our folks to use it.
那比方說我們民間拿來用更好用
For example, we just said that the communication software is broken
比方說我們剛才講通訊軟體壞掉
What to do if LINE is broken
LINE壞掉怎麼辦
LINE down doesn’t mean your internet is down
LINE壞掉不表示你的網路壞掉
Maybe it's just that his server is down
可能只是他server掛了
Maybe it's just that LINE was killed
可能只是LINE被被害了
or how
或者是怎麼樣
Well, it's software like this
好那可是像這個軟體呢
It doesn't matter you just need to connect to the Internet
它根本你只要網路通
Even if your network is not connected, it can pass through
甚至你網路不通它都能通
Well, you, so if you're in mission command
好那你所以你在做任務指揮的話
It's actually very useful
其實也很好用
Well, what this page actually tells you is
那這這頁其實跟大家講的是說
it has many uses
它有非常多的用途
And now you can start using
而且現在你就可以開始用了
The point is how much you you master it
那重點在於你你你對它的掌握有多少
Well, I just watched his video
好那剛才看的是他的影片
Is there an official video of him
有沒有他是官方的影片
Can you tell me that that can really work?
你可能講說那那那真的可以用嗎
It's just that he's because sometimes the film shows well
只是他他因為有的時候影片展示的很好
In fact, it can't be used
實際上就是用起來就不能用
So the first thing we do is we go and try
所以我們第一件事呢就是我們去試試看
We actually installed 40 basemaps
我們就真的裝了40個底圖
Make sure its basemap is available
確定它底圖是可以用的
We really did these synergies
我們真的做了這些協同
know each
知道每一個
Let's say this example
比方說這個例子好了
I was in Operation Blue Tit at Black Bear Academy
我那時候參加黑熊學院的藍雀行動
ok then what
好 然後呢
I'll just take two of us
我就我們就帶兩台去
Then one of the things that was played in the blue bird operation
然後那個藍雀行動裡面玩的一件事情
just anyway
就是就是反正
The People's Liberation Army is arresting people
解放軍在抓人抓人嘛
we just hide there
我們就在那邊躲躲躲
I got caught
結果我就被抓到了
after catch
抓到之後呢
I just look at the software
我就軟體就看起來
so i can know where my friends are
我就可以知道我的朋友在哪裡
so you know instantly where the other is
所以所以你即時知道對方在哪裡
It actually matters when something actually happens
其實在真正發生事情的時候很重要
those streams
那這些串流
Indeed, this thing can also move
確實這個東西也是會動的
Hardware and software integration
軟硬體整合
After we get acquainted with this
這個我們熟悉了之後
I know how to integrate
就知道是怎麼整合了
This page is actually very important
那這一頁其實很重要
that's it
就是它
it actually
它實際上
For example, you have a software like this
你比方說你一個類似這樣子的軟體
It says this is a tank
它裡面說這個是一個坦克
Then it says red is the enemy
那它比方說紅色就是敵軍
green may be allies
綠色可能就是友軍
then this tank
然後這個坦克
But the problem is you only look at tanks
可是問題是你光看坦克
It this for example this tank is
它這個比方說這個坦克是
which type
哪一型的
that is
就是說
It means that the icon you think is the same as the icon that others think
意思是說 你認為的icon跟別人認為的icon
See you both have to recognize the same thing
看到你們兩個要認知同樣的東西
No, he thinks the green is the friendly army, you think the green is the enemy, so what to do?
不能 他以為的綠色是友軍 你以為的綠色是敵軍 那怎麼辦
So the standard for the entire interface the standard for the entire format
所以 整個界面的標準 整個格式的標準
It's actually a very important thing
其實是一件很重要的事情
That's why it's important that he meets U.S. military standards
這就是他為什麼符合美軍標準很重要
I mean, any of you so-called, let's say, military-like people
意思是說 你任何所謂 比方說類似軍方的人
He sees this interface, he understands it at a glance
他看到了這個界面 他一看就懂
He won't need retraining and it's all the same
他不會 不需要再訓練 而且都一樣
Have relevant training
有相關訓練 好
This is just watched
這個是剛才看的
This is something really cool that we will find if we do GIS
這個是我們如果做GIS 其實就會發現很炫的東西
That is, since he can be here, like saying you are in the mountains
就是 他既然可以在 像說你在山裡
You can know that we are in the mountains, you can't see behind the mountains
我們在山裡你可以知道 山的後面你是看不到的
But how do you know that place you can see it or not
但是你怎麼知道那個地方 你看得到看不到
He's here, this place, where he stands in the middle
他在這裡 這個地方 他中間站的那個位置
Green is what he can see, red is what he can't see
綠色就是他看得到的 紅色就是他看不到的
may be blocked by mountains
可能被山擋住了
This is very useful when you are fighting, right?
這個你如果在戰鬥的時候就很有用了對不對
You can hit you, you can't hit you
你炮打得到你 打不到你
You have to see if you can hit or not
你要看看 或者你打得到 打不到對方
these are useful
這些都有用
Then this is task cutting
那這個是任務切割
I just saw this on video
這剛才都是影片上看過
I'm just going to say a little more here
我只是在這裡稍微再講一下
For example, this one on the right
比方說這個右邊這個
The one on the right is actually what it can be
右邊這個實際上它就是它可以
It means that you only need to connect in
等於是你只要連進去
you can message someone
你就可以跟別人發訊
So a group of people can communicate with each other
所以一群人裡面互相就可以通訊
It actually doesn't need a line or anything
它其實也不需要line 也不需要什麼
You just add it and you can basically do a group chat
你只要加進去 基本上就可以做群組通訊
What I saw just now were all other people's videos
那剛才看到的都是人家的影片
cutout of
的截出來的東西
Now let's show you an example of our own use
現在給大家看一下我們自己使用的實例
what is this example
這個例子是什麼
This example is that I took it and I went to Hualien to play
這個例子就是我拿著它 我去花蓮玩
It's not playing anymore
就 也不是玩了
just go to a meeting
就是去開會
When I go to a meeting, I will
去開會的時候呢 我就
Let's have a meeting. It's always delicious food in Hualien.
開個會嘛 總是花蓮好吃的東西
I'll just go eat and take a picture of it
我就去吃一吃嘛 順便把它照照相
What you can see is here
你可以看到的是在這裡
Never mind
就算了
You can see there is a ghost machine here, there are a lot of pictures
你可以看到這邊有鬼機 有很多的照片
Then the photos will be on the table
然後照片都會在圖台上
will show up showing it's a photo
會顯示出來 顯示它是一個照片
show its name
顯示它的名字
And more importantly, and you see this
然後更重要的是 而且你看這個
This so-called trajectory can be replayed
這個所謂的軌跡它都可以replay
means you can
就是說你可以
you can
你可以
Afterwards, you can know where you are at what time
事後你都可以知道你幾點幾分在哪裡
Where was the upper echelon at that time
那個時候的高層在哪裡
all this is known
這個全部都是知道的
More importantly, these whole packages
更重要的是這些整包的東西
it can be copied
它是可以複製下來的
I'll go to Hualien Wan to record this
我去花蓮丸把這個記錄下來
Then what
然後呢
when it's over i just push a button
結束的時候我只要按一個按鈕
Pack
打包
I'm just a bag
我就是一包了
Then I can pass this packet on to others
然後我這一包可以再傳給別人
so think about it
所以你自己想想看
Let's say we go do some scouting
假設我們去做一些探看
or do something
還是做一些什麼什麼事情
what you've done
你做完的東西
how do you give the information to others
你怎麼把資料交給別人
No, or a group of people working together
不行 或者是一群人一起合作
Suppose you collaborate to explore a thing
假設你合作去探索一件事情
Or let's say you cooperate to do an inventory
還是比方說你合作去盤點
where is it near here
這附近哪裡有
So your mask map is ready
所以你口罩地圖好了
Of course the masks were made very well.
口罩當初當然是做得很好
But the problem is when you don't have a mask system
但是問題是當你沒有口罩系統的時候
what are you going to do
你要怎麼辦
It's very simple to use this thing
用這個東西非常簡單
You just
你只要
Everyone has a machine like this
每一個人有這樣的機器
Then everyone's eyes should feel
然後應該大家眼睛會覺得
Let's say I'm in charge of taking inventory of this area.
那你比方說我負責盤點這一區
You are in charge of taking stock of that area
你負責盤點那一區
Hit everyone when they go
那每一個人去的時候就打他點點點
After I clicked, I took stock of the information
點完之後我盤點完的資料
I will pass it on to you
我就傳給你
and then both to the same person
然後都傳給同一個人
The same person has the right to merge the version
同一個人merge版他就有權份的
So that's where he's pretty good
所以這就是他相當厲害的地方
There is a picture in the middle
那這中間是有個畫面
Then this is like this picture
那又這個像這個畫面
he has many maps
他的地圖很多
For example, when climbing mountains, I like to use Lu map.
比方說登山就很喜歡用魯地圖
Then, for example, some folks are
然後比方說民間的有人就是
For example, if you want to see the river, you have to look at the government
比方說你想要看河的你就要看政府的
this kind of map
這種地圖
Then Google is everyone's favorite
那Google是大家比較喜歡的
Sometimes you want to watch satellites
有的時候你想要看衛星
Sometimes you want to look at drawings
有的時候你想要看圖紙
so many maps
那這麼多的地圖
He actually needs to be easily switched
他其實就是需要很容易的被切換
Then he can switch this thing at any time.
那這裡這個東西他就是隨時可以做切換
import at any time
可以隨時做匯入
the one on the upper right
那右上角的這個
This one in the upper right corner actually says
右上角這個實際上是說
He is the so-called packing
他就是剛才所謂的打包
That is, you can combine a lot of information into one package
就是你可以把很多的資訊都組成一包一包的
Just connect and download, after downloading, you will have all the information
連上來就下載 下載完你就有全部的資料
What's in this bag depends on what you packed in the first place.
那這一包裡面是什麼 就看你當初打包的是什麼
For example, you can let me give an example
比方說你可以 我舉例好了
Okay, here it is, right down the middle, it's the Water Resources Department.
好 這裡 這中間下面它就是水利署的
This is, for example, the data of the guards.
這種就是比方說警衛的資料
This is open data, so we import the open data directly.
這是開放資料 那我們就把開放資料直接匯進去
Others don’t have to do anything to get open information and get things
別人也不用去搞什麼 去拿開放資料拿東西
No, he just keeps coming in and opening it
不用 他只要一連進來 一打開它
There are guards all over his map
他的地圖上全部到處都有警衛
Let's say you think of it as, suppose you're all right now
那比方說你把它想成是 假設你這個時候戰亂好了
You have a supply point, all kinds of supply points
你有補給點好了 各式各樣的補給點
Now you probably have any supplies in there, you make it into a bag
那現在裡面大概有什麼補給品 你都把它弄成一包
As soon as the person enters the house, as soon as he opens it, there will be
那人家一進來 一打開就有
Where is he nearby? He is clear.
他在附近哪裡有 他清清楚楚的
that's where oral
那這就是 口用的地方
OK, let me tell you what we can do.
好 那我講一下我們能做什麼好了
First let me tell you who we are
首先先講一下我們是誰
Actually we are just us we play these things
其實我們就 我們這些 我們玩這些東西
Basically just a few people, a few engineers
基本上就是幾個人 幾個工程師
Some do system management, some do software development, some do hardware design
有做系統管理 有做軟體開發 有做硬體設計的
Experts with drones
有無人機的專家
Then our spirit is open source
然後我們的精神就是都是開放開源的
So you can see that the slideshow just now is open
所以你可以看到剛才的投影片是開放的
The links that you click on in the slideshow, everything is open.
那投影片點進去的連結 也所有東西都是開放的
All that we learn is open
那所有的 我們學到的東西都是開放的
what were we doing a while ago
那我們前陣子在做什麼
We call it free health account stacking
我們叫做免費的健帳堆練
For example, you are now listening to my talk about playing this thing
比方說你現在聽我講的玩這個東西
It feels good
感覺這個東西不錯啊
Is it easy to use?
那我要用很容易用嗎
Although it is enough to install it, will you use it after installing it?
雖然很足以就裝了 裝了你就會用嗎
In fact, when we played with this thing at the beginning, I found that
其實我們在一開始玩這個東西我發現
Actually it's not that easy
其實還沒那麼容易耶
it's a bit of a barrier to entry
它就有一點進入障礙
Mainly because I don't know why
主要是不知道為什麼就是
It's military software after all it's not enough
畢竟它就是軍隊的軟體 它不夠
It's well designed, but it's not clear enough
它雖然設計的很好 但是它不夠清明
it won't shoot you a youtube video saying
它不會給你拍一個YouTube的影片說
you just play like this
你就這樣玩就會了
Or you are hard to help with the manual
或者是你就說明書都硬幫幫的
dozens of pages like this
好幾十頁這樣子
you just think it's
你就覺得它就是
why 20 minutes
為什麼20分鐘
how to get it fast
怎麼快得到
Well, to put it simply
好 簡單講就是
Wired sparring We probably each
有線上對練 我們大概每個
every two to three weeks or a month
每兩三個禮拜或一個月
There's going to be an online duel so you can connect.
會辦一個線上對練 那你就可以連進來
Then you don't need to know anything, just take your
那你什麼都不用知道 你只要帶著你的
Enjoy the mobile phone to come in and it will be two hours
enjoy手機進來就好了 兩個小時
online you are in your own home within two hours
線上的 你在你自己家裡 兩個小時內
You promise to use it, that is, you will use the important things
你保證就會用了 就是重要的東西你都會用
We have such online sparring, I won’t talk about the others
我們有做這樣的線上對練 其他我就不講了
These are things that we've already done
這些是我們已經做的東西 其實
We do this online sparring, and it's very touching to say that
我們這樣做這個線上對練 令人很感動的就是說
We later had feedback that some police
我們後來有feedback說 有些警察
some policemen in their own
有些警察在他們自己的
I started using something like this in my work
勤務裡面就開始用這樣的東西
I said, how do you know this place? He said that it was you who held the online sparring.
我說那你們怎麼知道這裡 他說就是你辦那個線上對練
After they come in, they find it useful after they're done.
他們進來之後 完了之後覺得有用
I'll do it myself later, and then I'll do it
後面就自己搞 然後就搞起來了
So it's actually doable, it's proven to be doable
所以其實是可行的 這個是被證明是可行的
What does this have to do with digital willfulness? Today is not about digital willfulness.
這跟數位任性怎麼關係 今天不是講數位任性
In fact, it should be said that the community is very flexible.
其實應該講 社群是很彈性的
But the community is actually very unstructured.
但社群其實是很沒有結構的
And the most important thing is the structure
而且最重要是這個架構的東西
Difficult to compose in times of war
在遇到戰亂的時候是很難組成的
Architectural things take a lot of time to plan
架構的東西都是很花時間要規劃
what to build
要建構要幹嘛
Like the Su Hui diplomacy just now
像剛才那個蘇蕙外交
what they are doing
他們在做的東西
That's the architectural thing
這就是架構性的東西
your structural stuff
你這種架構性的東西
when you established very early
你在很早建立的時候
When something happens, everyone will come
當事情一發生所有人一摳就來
That's if you don't have this structure
那可是你如果沒有這個架構
you panic when it happens
你當事情發生的時候你就慌亂了
It's the same with this kind of software
那像這種軟體也是一樣
You usually play and practice
你平常的時候玩一玩練一練
well that might be used for paintball
好那可能用在打漆彈
What are you climbing again?
又在登山什麼
you preschool entertainment
你預教娛樂
but when it actually happens
但是實際上發生的時候
This time things are very useful
這個時候東西就很好用
let me tell you
那我來講一下
Let's not talk about this on the spot
這個就在現場就先不講了
because there is no time
因為已經沒時間了
I'll just talk about Uber
我就直接講Uber好了
while in ukraine
在烏克蘭的時候
that time they had a battle
那個時候他們有一個戰役
Just what, what, shield, Nez, what battle
就什麼什麼什麼盾內茲可什麼戰役
Then the black army is very strange
然後烏軍起席很奇怪
He suddenly one night at the same time
他突然一個晚上的同一個時間點
Didn't he say that all the tanks were blown up by him?
不是說所有坦克都被他炸毀嗎
I saw it then
那時候我看了就
just a headache
就很頭痛
Because we do information systems
因為我們做資訊系統的
we know very well
我們非常知道
it's very difficult
這非常難
How do you coordinate so much information
你怎麼協同這麼多的資訊
then let all the missiles
然後讓所有的飛彈
at the same gun at the same time
在同 炮在同一個時間
hit different tanks
打到不同的坦克上面
then they say
那他們就說
They're called the Uber system
他們叫做Uber系統
at that time we
那時候我們
we thought wow
我們就覺得哇
it's amazing
這很神奇
how the hell is this done
這到底是怎麼做的
found out later
後來發現
After I started to know this software
當我開始會這個軟體之後
Is this piece of cake good?
這piece of cake好不好
use this thing
用這個東西
no development at all
根本就不用開發
Here's how to do it
做方法就是這樣
Just say yes, everyone has
就說好 大家都有
let's say
那你比方說
we say in the message
我們在訊息裡面發說
we are at 4 a.m.
我們凌晨4點
we are going to shoot
我們要開炮
For example, this battlegroup
比方說這個戰鬥群組
4:00 a.m. I'm going to fire
凌晨4點我要開炮
it's 12 o'clock
現在12點
Commanders please yourself
請各指揮官你自己
Choose which tank you want to fight
選你要打哪一個坦克
That drone flew over
那無人機飛過去
he will find
他會找到
he will soar
他會飆
Bahia are these tanks here
飆是這些坦克在這裡
Then the commander would say, for example
然後指揮官就比方說
everyone chooses
大家就自選
After the election, someone must reveal it, right?
選完之後一定有人露的對不對
So he communicated in the group and said
所以他就在群組溝通說
so you hit him
那某你打他
he hit him
他打他
Okay, let's talk at 3:00
好 那大家3點都談
Don't move, everyone, start moving at 4 o'clock
大家都不要動,4點才開始動
4 o'clock, one hit is not all dead
4點一打不全死
It's that simple
就這麼簡單
no customization, no need for anything
也不用客製化,也不用什麼
The things just mentioned are all built-in in the AT software.
剛才講的那些東西在AT的軟體,全部都是內建
All do not need F, this is strong software and weak software
全部都不需要F,這就是強的軟體跟弱的軟體
You just saw this and you knew it
你剛剛光看到這件事你就知道
If you are fighting, you are
如果打戰的時候,你是
On the other side of Russia, you are
蘇俄那一端,你是
You are on the Russian side, you don't have this thing
你是俄國那一端,你沒有這個東西
Or do you wish you were Ukraine with this thing
還是你希望你是烏克蘭有這個東西
I don't want to be the one I don't have, I feel beaten to death
我覺得不希望我是沒有的那個,我覺得被人家打死了
This is, and most importantly, this is open
這種就是,而且最重要的是這個是開放的
That
那
This is the basic reference
這個就是基本上的參考資料
Anyway, this is pretty useful, but
反正這個蠻好用的,不過
I've always found it weird to promote this thing
我在推廣這件事的時候一直覺得很奇怪
he is open
他是開放的
no money
不用錢的
Then I don't know why everyone doesn't know
那我就不知道為什麼大家不知道
Then when I started learning this, I wanted to say I don't know
然後我一開始學這個,我想說不知道
It is because this one is very new, too new, so people don't know
就是因為這顆很新,太新了,所以大家不知道
no i touched his
不對,我接觸他的
He has been out for two or three years
他已經出來兩三年了
And what's more, I have been promoting him for more than half a year
然後更加是我已經推廣他很半年多了
In fact, I guess almost no one knows now.
其實我猜現在的人也幾乎沒有人知道
i feel weird
我就覺得很奇怪
Anyway, the most important thing is
反正這個最主要就是
The application promotion at the top is the first link at the beginning
最上面這個應用推廣就是剛開始的第一個連結
And the last practice guide is basically
然後最後那個實習練習指引基本上就是
when we practiced online
我們開線上對練的時候的
Record
記錄
Then if you say I can't wait for your online sparring
那你如果說我等不到你的線上對練
You click on the link below
你最下面那個連結點進去
In fact, if you follow that, you can already do it.
他實際上你照著那個做其實就已經可以做
Actually, you don't even need to come in to practice.
其實你也不用進來練
that's it
那就這樣子
ok 20 minutes yes yes yes
ok 20分鐘沒錯沒錯
thanks to his dad for sharing i think this
感謝他爸的分享我覺得這個
I just had this and secretly pressed download
我剛剛有這個偷偷按了下載
Sure enough, as you said, someone needs to be brought in the door
果然就像您說的需要有人帶進門
Anyway, wait a minute after our event
對反正等一下我們活動結束後
maybe a few minutes for us to be there
也許留個幾分鐘讓我們現場
This more people know this software
這個更多人認識這個軟體
But I think this thing is
但我覺得這個東西就是
Although we don't want
雖然我們不希望
we actually use it in wartime
我們真的在戰爭的時候用到它
because we don't want war
因為我們不希望發生戰爭
But actually the other way around
但是其實反過來講
Maybe the more people we had before the war even happened
也許越多人我們在戰爭還沒有發生之前
get ready for war
就做好戰爭的準備
War is less likely
戰爭更不容易發生
why? because you raised the enemy
為什麼?因為你提高了敵人
to attack your cost
要攻打你的成本
when he finds out
當他如果發現說
Whoever I'm going to attack is ready
我要攻打的對象都做好的準備
When my chances of success are low
我要成功攻佔的機率很低的時候
Otherwise, there will be no war
反而就不會發動戰爭了
So I think it's a
所以我覺得這是一個
why are we here now
我們現在為什麼在這裡
Another reason
另外一個原因
Then I think the one just before
那我覺得剛剛前面這個
whether habba
不管是Habba
Or we've had the holidays above and it's all good
或是我們過了以上的假期都很好
peacetime conversion
平戰轉換
In fact, many things we usually
那很多東西其實我們平常
We may all use things on a daily basis
我們也許日常都在使用東西
Maybe we didn't necessarily think to say
也許我們不一定有想到說
It turns out that this thing was during the war
原來這個東西在戰爭的時候
or in possibly gray
或是在可能灰色
When faced with the gray dangerous hybrid battle
面對灰色危險混合戰的時候
can come in handy
就可以拍上用場
So I think this is what we are looking forward to today
所以我覺得今天這個也是我們期待
Share with you the next details
下一個詳情跟大家分享
Because like Qsearch
因為像Qsearch
Meaning we are now very much
意思就是我們現在非常多
The industry is
這個業界都在
A community monitoring that will be used
會使用的一個社群監控
Or a tool to understand the voice of the community
或者了解社群聲量的一個工具
Then if there is a war
那如果碰到戰爭的時候
A monitoring tool for a community like this
像這樣的一個社群的一個監控工具
what kind of role can we play
可以幫我們扮演什麼樣的角色
I think this is worth listening to
我覺得這個很值得大家去聽聽看
Then let's welcome Director Cai first, thank you
那我們先歡迎蔡總監 謝謝
will there be a picture here
這邊會有畫面嗎
good
好
Hello everyone
大家好
Hello friends online
還有線上的朋友大家好
yes it is
對 就是
Like this one just lying on the tide
如同剛才臥潮的這個
In fact, we are the Cunzuo introduced by the chief operating officer Hong.
紅營運長介紹的其實我們就是存作
Monitoring of online information
線上的資訊的監控
That is of course based on public information.
那當然是以公開的資訊為主啦
Either that or I can already
不是那種就是我已經可以
Intrude into the conversation group that may be LINE
侵入到可能LINE的對話群組裡面
Actually, I'm still in the commercial field
像其實我還是在商業場
There will be some customers who have this kind of demand
會遇到一些客戶有這種需求
then i will call
那我就打去
just tell them
就跟他們說
Maybe join the official organization on the other side
或許加入對岸的官方組織
You will have this opportunity to enjoy this right like this
你會有這個機會享受這個權利這樣子
Yes, but we still don't have this thing in Taiwan
對 但是在台灣我們還是沒有這件事情的
So we're collecting a lot of publicly available information
那我們就是收集大量公開的資訊
That's actually because now
那其實因為現在
I believe everyone feels the information explosion
我相信大家都覺得資訊爆炸
Especially in recent times, there are too many
尤其最近這一段時間又超多的
Various information about a series of societies
各種對 連串的社會的資訊
it just keeps happening
就是一直在發生這樣子
And so actually some people
然後 所以其實有些人
That's when the information can be too explosive
就是資訊可能太爆炸的時候
he is easily distracted or frustrated
他就很容易分心或懊弱
Or it's just that he can't absorb it like this
或者說就是他難以吸收這樣子
That's too far
那 扯遠了
Let's go back to today's topic
我們就還是回到今天的講題
Then introduce our company first
那先介紹一下我們公司
That is to say, when it comes to cognitive operations,
就是說 其實講到認知作戰
In fact, the election campaign is also a cognitive war
其實選戰也是一個認知作戰
Then we are indeed the space-time background of software development
那我們的確這個軟體發展的時空背景
It happened to be 2014
剛好是2014年
that year
那那年
It's the mayoral race
就是市長的選戰
That's a motley crew
那是一個算是雜牌軍
A motley crew with a consensus
大家有一個共識的一個雜牌軍
That's against another candidate Lian Shengwen like this
那對抗了另外一個候選人連勝文這樣子
In that year, I thought I should remind everyone of the background of time and space.
那一年我覺得要提醒大家那個時空背景
In fact, Facebook did not have a large number of commercial advertisements in that year.
其實那一年Facebook還沒有大量的商業的廣告出現
Even many brands have not yet established a fan industry
甚至很多品牌都還沒建立粉絲業
what is the reason
原因是什麼呢
They were still stealing vegetables back then.
那時候都還在偷菜啊
or the end of the restaurant
或者說什麼餐廳的末期
Everyone is still playing online games
大家還在玩網路遊戲
yes but it is
對 可是就是
just because you know
就是因為你也知道就是
Candidate Ke Wenzhe did not have so many resources at that time
柯文哲候選人在那時候沒有那麼多的資源
He may have political ideas or something
他有可能政治的理念什麼的
Then he will call a group of people
那他就要號召了一群人
Then these people started using the Internet
那這群人開始利用網路
Platforms like this are starting to advocate
這樣子的平台開始去倡議
then go tell everyone
然後去告訴大家說
then this is one such candidate
那這是一個這樣的候選人
what is the ideal of this candidate
這個候選人的理想是什麼
So what are his expectations for the municipality?
那他對於市政的一些期待是什麼
or what will he do in the future
或者他未來會怎麼做
Then you see he is doing cognitive warfare
那你看他就是在認知作戰
He's just telling everyone
他就是在告訴大家說
then why do you support me
那為什麼你要支持我
So in fact, the market share of the campaign brand
所以其實選戰品牌的市佔率
He is cognitive warfare
他都是認知作戰
Of course there are some confrontations between countries
那當然國與國之間的一些對抗
He is also a cognitive operator
他也是一個認知作戰
It just means that we usually compare
那只是說我們平常可能比較
I think this distance is far
覺得這個距離比較遠
Or rather don't know how to deal with
或者說比較不知道怎麼應對
so maybe on this
所以可能在這上面
I think the better way
我覺得比較好的方式
It's our open discussion
就是我們來公開的討論
Then see how
然後看有怎樣的做法
Can go for drills and upgrades
可以去演練和升級
optimize your awareness
優化自己的這個意識
ok that pair
好 那對
just to introduce
就是剛剛介紹一下
We started in 2014
我們是從2014年開始
collect this information
蒐集這些資料
There was Facebook in the beginning
那一開始就有Facebook嘛
That's quite a lot now
那現在的確就是蠻多的
Actually we're not just political type clients
其實我們不只是政治類型的客戶
Mainly commercial customers
主要還是商業客戶為主
the needs of commercial customers
那商業客戶的需求
Still contains quite a lot of other media
還是有包含了蠻多其他的媒體
For example, in recent years, IG YouTube
譬如說近幾年IG YouTube
In fact, more and more users like this
其實都是越來越多這樣子的使用者
that or
那或者說
online forums
線上的這些論壇
Things like PTD cards
像PTD卡這些東西
There is still a need for business intelligence gathering
都還是有商業情報收集的需求
So we just collected more and more complete data
所以我們就是收集了越來越齊全的資料
Of course we also collected some
那當然我們也有收集一些
Transnational facebook information
跨國的一些facebook的資料
just indeed
只是的確
Operate as a commercial company
以商業公司營運上面
It does require some user use
它的確需要一些使用者的使用
So we're balancing this thing
所以我們就是在平衡這件事情
good
好
That's exactly what it's doing
那的確就是在做的是
Develop Parchong software
開發帕蟲軟體
then collect data
然後收集資料
Then build a visual interface
然後建構一個視覺化的界面
I'm sure you're all using Google
那我相信大家都有使用Google
So what Google gives you is its guess
那Google給你的就是它推測
You may be interested in these pages
你可能對於這些網頁
do you charge a key
你收一個關鍵是嗎
There is a need, and what I want to know
是有需求的是想要了解的這樣
so it recommends
所以它就推薦
EatLocku webpage for you
EatLocku網頁給你
then our side
那我們這邊
Even Google it does something like
甚至Google它會做一些就是
how to say
怎麼講
It guesses you might take the A word
它推測你可能收A字
But it speculates that the B word is also related to the A word
但是它推測B字跟A字也有關
So it might put the word B in some pages that contain
所以它可能把B字的一些包含的網頁
push you like this
都推給你這樣子
Our main service here is organizations or brands, which are related to business
我們這邊主要服務的是組織或者說品牌這種跟商業
Or maybe the operator of the cognitive warfare just mentioned
或者說可能剛剛講的認知作戰的操作方
in this way
這樣子
That means they may need more precise information
那就是說他們可能需要比較精確的資料
For example, today I may be President Tsai Ing-wen
譬如說我今天可能蔡英文總統
then he has many aliases
那他有很多別名
Then I will call up one by one
那我就要一一打上來
Then go collect these posts that contain these keywords
然後去收集這些有包含這些關鍵字的貼文
I can't use a blur to show the user something like this
我不能用模糊的東西給使用者看這樣子
So we actually developed a visual interface
所以我們其實開發了一個視覺化界面
Then the difference between him and Google is that
然後他跟Google的差別在於說
he is pictorial
他是有圖像化的
He can tell you some comparisons
他是可以告訴你說量的一些比對的
So what are some of the more influential posts?
那或者說可能一些比較有影響力的貼文是什麼
Then I will show you some pictures later
那我待會會受一些畫面給大家看
Of course, it is for the fact that I just came here before
那當然針對就是其實我剛來之前
I was listening to another professor's speech
我是聽另外一個教授的演講
He is a professor at National Taiwan University
就是台大資工的教授
Then he said that AI is very popular now
那他說現在AI很盛行
Then AI is actually like our children
那AI其實就是像我們小
Maybe when I was studying
以前讀書的時候可能就是
Do you need to turn the pages to look up the dictionary?
查字典什麼的還要翻書嘛
then progress to
那現在就進步到
Hey, maybe an invincible translator
欸可能無敵翻譯機啊
From now on, mobile phone can check anytime
然後到現在手機隨時可查
In fact, information is now very easy to obtain.
那其實現在資訊已經非常容易取得了
Rather, it is whether everyone's analytical ability has kept up
那反而是大家的分析能力有沒有跟上
that or
那或者說
Hey, in fact, some AI is being trained now
欸其實現在有訓練一些AI
it can be
它可以就是
put some mature analysis
把一些成熟的分析
logical or path can turn it into a
邏輯或路徑可以把它變成一個
Common people can also use it like this
一般人也可用的這樣子
is that it may use a simple interface for everyone to use
就是它可能用一個簡易的介面讓大家使用
that's just saying in
那只是說在
Well
呃
The so-called cognitive warfare
所謂的認知作戰這塊
In fact, it is still difficult
其實目前還是有點難以
just have one
就是有一個
Relatively fixed analysis logic
比較固定的分析邏輯
because sometimes
因為有時候其實
Uh, the speaker or the party who tried out the message
呃發言方或者說把這個訊息試出來這一方
what is its position
它的立場是什麼
it may be a variable
它可能是一個變動的
Then it can be done in a very diverse way
然後呢它的作法可能非常多元
So in fact, we address some needs of customers
所以其實我們針對客戶的一些需求
for example maybe in
譬如說可能在
An analysis of an issue, or a
一個議題的分析啊或者說一個
uh yes
呃就是
Some analysis of business needs
商業的需求的一些分析
We are still relatively high in human intervention
我們都還是人力的介入比較高
So we also provide a consultant service like this
所以我們也有提供一個顧問的服務這樣子
To help customers do some data induction and analysis
去幫客戶去做一些資料的歸納整理和解析
Our interface just mentioned is like this
那剛才說到的我們介面就像這樣
The one on the left is an interface gradually entered from 2014 to now
像左邊這個就是從2014年到現在逐步進進的一個介面
It's a search engine like Google
它就是跟Google同樣是搜尋引擎
It's just that the information we searched was all social media forums.
只是我們搜的資料都是社群媒體論壇
Or information such as electronic media
或者說電子媒體這樣的資料
then we just visualize it
那我們就是把它視覺化
For example, now there is volume
譬如說現在有聲量
What does the volume mean?
那聲量就是怎麼代表
Because before the community came out, the definition of volume was the volume of articles
因為社群出來之前就是聲量的定義是文章量
But now the definition of volume should be the volume of attention
可是現在聲量的定義應該是關注量
That is, how many people interacted with this Facebook post
就是說Facebook這篇貼文有多少人互動
Indicates how much attention this person has paid to this post
代表這個人這個貼文的關注程度是多少
In the past, electronic media or paper media
那以前的電子媒體或者說紙媒
In fact, it is difficult for you to know that you may look at the circulation
其實你很難知道你可能看發行量
You may see that it is online media, it may have public
你可能看就是網路媒體它可能有公開
what pageviews
什麼瀏覽量
But have these pageviews been verified
但是這些瀏覽量有沒有經過核實際
don't know
也不知道這樣子
So in fact, it will be difficult for you to know the influence of a content
所以其實你會很難知道一個內容的影響力
But social media is relatively organic.
可是社群媒體它相對來說有機可尋嘛
That is to say, this post is like refueling, I just said it
就是說這個貼文像加油剛剛有說嘛
just maybe a ukrainian
就是可能一個烏克蘭人
just shared a post about him in Ukraine
就是分享了一個他在烏克蘭的貼文
How many people follow
那有多少人關注
We can learn from those numbers organically
我們可以從那些數字有機可尋知道
How many people are paying attention to this matter
有多少人在關注這件事情
Yes, so we are presenting in this way
對 所以我們就是在用這樣的方式去呈現說
Oh that issue
喔 那一個議題
It appears in which pipelines have this topic mentioned
它出現在哪些管道有提到這個議題
Then how many people interacted with the posts mentioning this issue in these channels
然後這些管道提到這個議題的貼文有多少人互動
We visualize it like this
我們就這樣子視覺化的呈現出來
Okay, so here's how we organize our information
好 所以這是我們資訊整理的方式
that's really in business
那的確在商業上面
Will also do some combat dashboards
也會做一些戰情儀表版
because maybe it is
因為可能它是
Whether it is a commercial brand
不管是一個商業的品牌
or say a candidate
或者說一個候選人
it also says the same
它一樣也都是說
Hey, I'm in every channel
欸 我在各管道
How many people interacted with
到底引起多少人的互動
It is presented with a combat dashboard
就是用一個戰情儀表版呈現出來
That way it will be quick
那這樣子就可以很快的
I know what state I'm in now
知道說我現在在怎樣的狀態
Then which direction should I work hard
那我要往哪個方向努力
Or who is kinder to me
或者說哪些人對我比較有善
Who is less friendly to me
哪些人對我比較不友善
I can use this way
我就可以透過這樣的方式
comparison at a glance
比較一目了然
Then of course we also take these things apart
那當然我們也把這些東西拆碎
That is, it can also be combined with different
就是說它也可以結合到不同的
in internal system
內部系統中
Then or directly use the API to connect with others
然後或者說直接用API跟別人對接
Okay, that's about the end of my company introduction.
好 那大概介紹完我公司
I'm just more relevant today
我就是跟今天比較有關係
still continue
還是延續
Anyway, everyone may understand the election campaign better.
反正選戰大家可能比較理解
so leave
所以離開
so many legislators
就是這麼多立委
In fact, there are many legislators
其實立委就是非常多
that everyone uses social media
那每個人都有利用社群媒體
In fact, now using the political capacity of social media
其實現在利用社群媒體的政治容量
Very almost like maybe 90% 100%
非常幾乎就是可能90% 100%的這樣子
Then they actually sent a lot of questions.
那他們其實都發了非常多問
But you and I believe not everyone
可是你我相信不是每個人
Every article is tracked
都每篇文都追蹤到
Yes, these legislators are dealing with
對 那這些立委主公都是在處理
Everyone is digesting everyone's tax budget
大家就是消化大家的納稅預算
Then go to deal with the affairs of the country
然後去處理國家的大事
yeah that's just saying
對 那只是說
time you might normally live
你可能平常生活的時間
you will not
你不會
uh spent so much time chasing down say
呃 花那麼多時間去追蹤說
Hey, are these people doing something good?
欸 這些人是不是有好處事
That may be what everyone expected in the past to say
那可能過去大家期望的是說
We use uh some citizen media to track these people
我們用呃 一些公民媒體來去追蹤這些人
Are you doing well?
有沒有好好的辦事
But now it's true that citizen media himself demands survival
但現在的確公民媒體他自己也要求生存
That is to say, he also wants to have a commercial hidden pregnancy.
就是說他也要商業隱孕這樣子
So I, I would think that actually after social media came out,
所以我 我會覺得說其實社群媒體出來之後
Uh, the media industry has changed from being very centralized to a very decentralized structure
呃 媒體這個產業就從非常集中到了一個很分散式的結構
That's why we're here today to discuss this
那這也是為什麼今天我們要在這裡討論這個
The problem is that in the past, the ability of the media to try may not have been that important
題目就是說過去其實媒體試圖能力可能沒有那麼重要
Because you can't change the structure of that media
因為你也沒辦法改變那個媒體的結構
But now the power of the media is important because now who
但是現在媒體試圖能力變得很重要是因為現在誰
Once a message comes out, everyone may go crazy or something.
一個訊息出來大家可能就會瘋傳什麼的
then you need to understand
那你就更需要去理解說
Hey, what is the purpose of this message?
欸 這個訊息傳出來的意圖是什麼
how could he affect me like this
他可能怎麼影響我這樣子
Yes, the words here mean uh
對 那這裡的話就是說呃
you read so much information
你看那麼多的資訊
Then who will subtract and sum the information?
那到底這些資訊誰來減和
Then what impact does he have on society?
然後呢他對於社會造成什麼影響
certainly
當然
As the previous two mentioned, it means different roles
如同前面兩位提到就是說不同角色
We can play our respective positions in this social structure
我們可以在這個社會結構扮演各自的崗位
and do these things well
然後把這些事情做好
For example, there are indeed some
譬如說的確有一些
We regularly collate this information
我們定期會整理這些資訊
and make it available to everyone
然後讓大家可以取用
Or make some observations about possible legislators
或者說做一些可能立委主公的觀察
Then what about these legislators?
然後呢或者說這些立委主公他們
This topic will be mentioned differently
會提到不同的這個議題
Which issues are actually getting more attention from the public?
那哪些議題其實比較受到民眾的關注
Then we are through the classification and labeling of these posts
那我們就是透過這些貼文的分類和標記
and then take the influence of these so-called post interactions
然後把這些所謂的貼文互動的影響力
do a calculation
去做一個計算統計出來
After that, it ran out of a chart like this
之後就是跑出這樣子的圖表
Let everyone go for reference
讓大家去參考
Of course, part of the legislator's purpose is to meet some expectations of the voters.
那當然立委他一部分是要滿足選民的一些期望
Then of course he has to meet the party's expectations.
那他當然也要去滿足黨的期望
Or maybe it's on his own personal will
或者說可能在這個他自己個人意志上面
to do a balance like this
去做一個平衡這樣子
So we can go this way
所以我們可以透過這樣的方式去
Assist in calibration
協助校正
Some expectations that people have about potentially different objects
大家對於可能不同對象的一些期望
and then go so that they can optimize themselves like this
然後去讓他們可以更優化自己這樣子
yes that looks like you
對 那像你看
Issues of particular concern to the opposition and ruling parties
在野黨和執政黨他們特別關注的議題
The issues he used to fight may be different
他拿來打的議題可能又不一樣
or his voters
或者說他的選民
his district voters
他的區域選民
In other words, the degree of attention of his supporters is not the same.
或者說他的支持者的關注的程度也不太一樣
That's how we grab these articles
那我們就是把這些文章就是這樣抓出來
Then there are a lot of them, maybe tens of thousands
然後很大量嘛 大概上前上萬則
Then we classify it
然後我們就把它分類
It should be tens of thousands
應該是說上萬則嘛
So sort it and go tag it
那把它分類 然後去打標
Then make an analysis chart of influence like this, and it will look like this
然後再做這樣子的影響力的分析圖出來這樣子
Yes, of course would want to automate this
對 那當然會想要把這個自動化
So we also have in the test say
所以我們也一樣有在測試說
Can AI speed up this process?
AI是不是可以加速這件事情的進行
less involvement
讓人的參與程度可以比較少
Because we are constructing an analysis logic
因為我們就是在建構一個分析邏輯出來
That allows everyone to supervise faster and more efficiently
那讓大家可以更快的更有效率的去監督
These are the people who are chosen
這些就是人選之人這樣子
ok that pair
好 那對
These are some of the presentations we made with the data we crawled
這些都是我們用我們爬到的資料去做的一些這樣子的呈現
Then everyone can see that
那大家就可以看到說
That's actually quite interesting.
那有些其實很有趣啊
for some reason he happens a lot
有些理由他發生很多
But his influence may not be that great relatively
但是他的影響力可能相對來說沒有那麼大
probably based on charisma based on the issues he speaks about
可能基於個人魅力基於他講的議題
Based on the trust he may have built up with voters in the past or something
基於他可能過去對於選民建立的信任感還是什麼的
will affect the results of these things
都會影響到這些東西的結果
He will keep changing dynamically like this
他會動態的一直變化這樣子
Yes, so it is true that the information tube is very explosive when there is a lot of information.
對 所以的確資訊管到很多資訊也很爆炸
Then we need to have some effective way to organize
那我們就需要有一些有效的方式來整理
Well, it just so happened that a lot of things like this happened this year.
那這是剛好就是今年也發生很多這樣的事情嘛
Then we have also made some comparative issues for the release of these contents
那我們也有做一些比較議題面向的這些內容的發布
that is to say
那就是去看說
How about the traffic problem on the Internet?
那交通問題網路上面怎麼炒嘛
Then how do you pay attention
然後大家怎麼關注嘛
Did the level of everyone's attention follow the occurrence of some events?
那大家關注的程度有沒有隨著一些事件的發生
while rising
而上升啊
Or maybe there are some sub-topics under this big topic
或者說可能在這個大議題底下有一些子議題
What are you discussing about those sub-topics?
那些子議題大家又在討論什麼
What kind of words are mentioned like this
提及什麼樣的字眼這樣子
Then sort it out in this way so that everyone can understand it better.
那就透過這樣的方式去整理出來讓大家比較好理解
Because I believe that when you're dealing with very large
因為我相信當你面對非常大量
For example, you may give up reading 10,000 articles
譬如說一萬篇文章你可能就放棄閱讀
But these 10,000 articles seem to be sorted out for you
但是這一萬篇文章好像有人幫你整理好
You'll feel like I'm coming to see it like this
你就會覺得我來看看這樣子
That threshold will be much different
那個門檻就會差很多
that's what we're doing
那我們就是在做這樣的事情
for citizens like this
for公民這樣子
Or maybe some of the media's docking objects like this
或者說可能一些媒體的這樣子的對接的對象
Then you should pile on this cognitive warfare
那應堆這個認知作戰
It's just that I just mentioned a little earlier
就是我剛剛稍微前請提要
That is, we are faced with a large amount of information
就是我們就是面對大量資訊
We do some tidying up
我們做一些整理 梳理的方式
That part of course tries to automate
那當然一部分嘗試自動化
Part of it is still human-involved, and the part looks like this
一部分還在人力參與很多的部分這樣子
then in this state
那在這個狀態下
In fact, it also requires the cooperation of many different units of objects
其實也需要很多不同的單位的對象來協力
that for the government
那以政府來說
Because in fact, this kind of social platform in Taiwan
因為其實台灣的這種社群平台
mostly foreign
大部分都是國外的
Then I think there are quite a few incidents
那我想就是有蠻多的事件
it happens all the time
也一直在發生嘛
For example, did you see someone impersonate?
譬如說你看有人冒名嗎
just a lot
就是很多
I show up right after something happens
我發生事情之後就馬上出現
Scam syndicates are doing penis comparisons
詐騙集團都做得比較陰莖
Immediately there is an impostor etc.
馬上出現一個冒塌名等
Then he said hey, you can join my LINE group
然後說 欸 加入我的LINE群可以
It's like the stocks are fat and high.
就是股票肥高高之類的
yes so actually
對 所以其實
I think the government is on top of this
我覺得政府在這上面
Need to pay attention to these social platforms
需要去關注這些社群平台
How to raise possibly some malicious messages
如何提高可能一些惡意訊息
The operating threshold looks like this
操作的門檻這樣子
For example, how about
那譬如說怎麼樣子
Distinguish, compete for position, these things
辯識 爭位啊這些東西
They need to actively discuss with the platform
他們需要積極跟平台方去做討論
and that is
以及就是
Target some influential KOLs
針對一些有影響力的KOL
or influencer
或者說influencer
In fact, he may have been in these people in the past
其實這些人過去他可能就是在
The framework of traditional media to operate
傳統媒體的框架去運作
That may be relatively manageable in
那可能相對來說可以控制在
to a certain extent it won't be
一定的程度 不會就是
speak indiscriminately or speak indiscriminately quickly
胡亂發言或者說胡亂發言很快
can be controlled
就可以受到控制
But now because of the platform, everyone can use it freely
但現在因為平台大家都可以自由運用
then i feel like saying
那我會覺得說
he's like what we usually do
他就像我們平常做那種
Disaster drills are the same
防災演練一樣 就是
These guys have to be more interesting
這些人必須要更有意思
Because he's a man of influence
因為他是有影響力的人嘛
He must be more interesting to know that he is in this society
他必須要更有意思的去知道自己在這個社會中
What is the role of delivering information
傳遞資訊的角色是什麼
Then he has to be more interesting to prevent some
那他也要更有意思的去防止一些
The spread of wrong or malicious information
不對的訊息或是說惡意的訊息的擴散
Yes, then I think this is where the government can go
對 那我覺得這是政府可以去
plan some resources and then
規劃一些資源 然後
Identify influencers on the platform
辨識一下平台上有影響力的人
and then encourage them to participate in something like this
然後去鼓勵他們參與這樣子的
workshop or walkthrough like this
工作坊或演練這樣子
Make them more media literate
讓他們更有媒體識讀能力
Because in fact, for such an influential person
因為其實對於這種有影響力的人
Sure wish he was more media literate.
當然希望他更有媒體識讀能力嘛
Otherwise they do whatever they want
不然他們隨便亂做
Then the general public will accept it
那一般民眾就接收嘛
Because the content is actually created by a small number of people
因為其實創造內容的是少數人
that most of the people are the ones who receive the content
那大部分人是接收內容的人
Then for these more influential nodes
那針對這些比較有影響力的節點
Of course there are more things to do
當然要做比較多的事情
Then again, it is true that the government regularly visits
那再來是說的確政府就是定期去
Minus and these influential people
減和這些具備影響力的人
and then go to the list
然後把它去依羅列出來
Then also subtract and say they used to pass the comparison
然後也減和說他們過去在傳遞比較
The status of the message in question
有問題的訊息的這個狀況
what is the extent of the situation
狀況的程度是怎麼樣子
Of course we can construct this logic
當然我們可以把這個邏輯建構起來
Then do a certain degree of regulation
然後去做一定程度的監管
I'm not here to talk about regulation
不是我這邊講到監管
Not to stop everyone or say
不是說阻止大家或者說
Control people not to speak freely
控制大家不能自由發言
but that you remind him
而是說你要提醒他
something is wrong
有些東西不對
then you may want to train him
那你可能要訓練他
to correct or say
去改正或者說
train him
訓練他
probably try not to have something like this happen
可能盡量不要發生這樣的事情
the media and influencers
那媒體和影響力人士
Indeed, he just became
的確他就是變成說
Create some messages and produce and disseminate
建立一些訊息和製作和散播的
check mechanism
檢核機制
Right now there are a lot of PR crises like now
馬上像現在有很多公關危機
it happened to some famous people
就是發生在一些名人身上
Then why is this situation?
那這個狀況其實為什麼呢
Because in the past they faced traditional media
因為過去他們面對的是傳統媒體
That node is relatively simple
那個節點是相對簡單的
but now you are
可是現在你是
After posting a lot of things online
很多東西發上網之後
I can't get it back
就收不回來了
Then he started spreading out
然後他就開始擴散出去
So actually a lot of people are on it
所以其實很多人在這上面
unconscious
沒有意識
He will feel that I can say whatever I want to say
他就會覺得說我要講什麼就講什麼
Is it a free society?
是不是自由社會嗎
Then he didn't expect to say
然後他就沒有意料到說
because it was caused after he sent it out
因為他發出去之後造成的
how big is this
有多大多大這樣
So it's actually suspicious.
所以其實這個東西是詳疑的嘛
that is
就是說
people in the media industry or
媒體同業的人或是說
he is influential
他是有影響力的人士
he has to be more conscious
他必須要更有意識
Facing the matter of being influential
面對自己是有影響力這件事情
Then he needs to know more about his message
然後他要更知道說自己的訊息的
some checks and controls
一些檢核和控制的機制
What is the mechanism of self-correction?
自我修正的機制是什麼這樣子
For some dissemination of news from time to time
那針對不時訊息的一些散播
how to face
要怎麼樣子面對
Well, he actually has a little
那他其實也有一點
Public relations image training?
公關形象的訓練嘛這樣子
Then establish some cooperation mechanism with the government platform
然後與政府平台建立一些協作機制嘛
Because in fact these large nodes
因為其實這些大的節點
It is also easy to receive messages from various parties
也很容易收到一些各方的訊息
Do you want to report these messages?
那這些訊息要不要通報
Or should we assist in joint governance?
或者說要不要協助共同治理
Maybe something is wrong on the platform
可能平台上出現一些不對的東西
to co-govern or something
要共同治理什麼的
I think this can be actively discussed like this
這我覺得是可以積極討論這樣
What about the general public?
那一般民眾呢
Of course, there are not many tools available.
當然可以用的工具就不多啦
Because in fact these platforms
因為其實這些平台
Of course he's in free mode
他當然是免費模式嘛
That is to use everyone to make money.
那就是把大家只要拿來賺錢這樣
So in fact, I think the general public
那所以其實我覺得一般民眾
to face is
要面對的是
How to develop the ability to try
如何去培養試圖能力
Then I divide it into two categories
那我又分成兩類
Divided into two categories
初分成兩類啊
Some of them are practitioners like us or
一部分就是像我們這種從業人或是說
Familiar with numbers
用數位用的比較熟悉的
He has digital ability and digital sensitivity.
他就是數位能力數位敏感度比較高的
What about this kind of person?
那這種人呢
is relatively speaking
就是相對來說
Doesn't need a lot of training
不太需要大量的訓練嘛
But actually we
可是其實我們
That is, the population structure has become an inverted triangle
就是人口結構已經變成倒三角形
I think the statistical results
我覺得就統計學的結果
In fact, most elders are relatively
其實大部分的長輩是比較
Those who are not familiar with these digital environments
不太熟悉這些數位環境的
Yes, I didn't want
對 就是我沒有要
means discrimination
就是歧視的意思
But this is the result of statistics
但是這是統計的結果
is that you can see that it is
就是你可以看到說就是
If you continue to report a lot, you will be deceived like this.
繼續報導很多就是這樣子被騙嘛
In fact, I think it has something to do with finances and some personal perceptions.
其實我覺得跟財務跟個人的一些認知都有關係
So actually I would say
所以其實我會覺得說
Do your parents take care of themselves?
自己的爸媽自己顧嘛
Or maybe my relatives and friends take care of themselves
或者說可能自己的親友自己顧
that or
那或者說
Maybe the government or related units can use these resources
可能政府或者說相關的單位可以利用這些資源
Education that popularizes these digital literacy
普及這些數位知識的教育
help everyone to identify
幫助大家去辯認說
that this
那這
Background tea box for some influential objects
一些影響力的對象的背景茶盒
that is
就是說
then a message today
那今天一個訊息來
Then you can first see who the speaker is
那你可以先看一下發言者是誰
is he an imposter
他是不是冒名的
Or what purpose does he have?
還是他是有什麼樣的目的
What
什麼的
just make it a habit
就是可以養成這樣的習慣
I give an example
我舉個例子
In fact, like in the past, Facebook targeted every fan industry
其實像過去Facebook針對每個粉絲業
he didn't offer
他沒有去提供
so-called transparency
所謂的透明度的
information field like this
這樣子的資訊欄位
But after some election turmoil
可是在某些選戰發生亂子之後
Has the fan industry changed its name?
那這個粉絲業有沒有改過名稱
Which area is his manager from?
他的管理者是哪個區域的人
can be directly compared to transparent
都可以直接相對於透明一些
then i think
那我覺得
But what he did
可是他做的這件事情
Not everyone has this habit
不是所有人都有這樣的習慣
to check this thing
去查這件事情
So many people still see
所以還是很多人看到說
this person posted
這個人發文
heard of this person
聽過這個人
I believe what he wrote
我就相信他發的文了
it will still happen
還是會有這樣的狀況發生
That's people with poor digital sensitivity.
那就是數位敏感度比較差的人
that kind of person
那這種人
We can only remind him
我們只能藉由提醒他
Train him to raise awareness like this
訓練他來讓他們提高這樣的意識
Then I think this is something the general public can do.
那我覺得這是一般民眾可以做的事情
He has less tools
像他來說工具比較少
because
因為
The analysis tool department also has to learn the threshold like this
分析工具系也要去學習門檻這樣子
right good
對 好
In the past, the role of the media was indeed
那像過去的確媒體的角色就是
Maybe help with vacation?
可能幫忙打假嘛
That is they have something like this reporter
那就是他們有一些像這次報導者
He just went to see how to spread some malicious messages.
他就是去看說一些惡意訊息怎麼散播啊
And what is his impact on society?
然後他在對社會的影響是什麼啊
then what are those sources
然後那些來源是什麼
That is indeed a comparison
那的確這就是比較用
The so-called intelligence officer looks at the dissemination of these messages from a more overlooked perspective.
所謂的情報官比較俯瞰的角度去看這些訊息的流傳
but you as a facebook user
可是你身為一個facebook的使用者
You just take the message and you believe it
你就是接收訊息你就相信了
that for this kind of person
那對於這種人
What about this kind of people?
對於這種民眾呢
People with low digital sensitivity
數位敏感度比較差的民眾
Of course we can only remind him and train him.
我們當然只能去提醒他 訓練他
like me may be more mandatory
像我可能就是比較強制性的
It is possible that my mother passed on some
我媽傳一些就是可能
I think it's the source of the content farm
我覺得是內容農場的來源的
I just help him block these sources on facebook regularly
我就直接幫他定期的在facebook封鎖這些來源
It's more mandatory to do this.
就是比較強制性的做這件事情
Because it costs you too much to train him
因為你要訓練他的成本太高了
You might as well just help him deal with it like this
你還不如直接幫他處理處理這樣子
Of course, this is how it can cover some
那當然就是這樣子就可以蓋掉一些
Possibly not a very good quality message
可能不是太好的品質的訊息
in this way
這樣子
that or
那或者說
You see my friend did encounter this time
你看我的朋友的確也遭逢了這一次的
chaotic
紛亂
that is there is a wrong message
那就是有一個不對的訊息
stuffed into one
塞到了一個
the mouth of the most recent topic
最近的話題人物的嘴裡
The person in question didn't say anything about it.
那那個話題人物的確也沒有說這件事情
But the victim
但是這個受害者就
It may be thought by some netizens that
就被可能一些網友覺得說
Are you lying to me?
你是不是騙我啊
Are you really busy?
你是不是真的全忙啊這樣子
That's true being an influencer
那的確身為影響力人士
It should be my second point
就是會應該我講的第二點
That is to say, he can only quickly clarify
就是說他只能快速的澄清
and use some good
並且用一些好的
Compared with the low-threshold method
比較門檻低的方式
Let everyone quickly understand
讓大家快速的了解說
Then why am I not what you say
那為什麼我不是你們說的那樣
or as you know
或你們認知的那樣子
then i think it's a celebrity
那我覺得這是名人的
or influential nodes
或者說有影響力的節點
some training like this
一些訓練這樣子
Then or you look at ancient times
然後或者說你看古來其實
also in this wave
也在這波有去
Let everyone pay attention to this matter
讓大家關注這件事情嘛
Said that Facebook in Taiwan is in charge of advertising
說那台灣臉書是管廣告的
But
可是
Why are they still unable to manage efficiently?
他們為什麼至今還是沒辦法有效率的管理呢
Is there still some room for optimization?
那是不是還有一些優化的空間
I think he is proposing this topic
我覺得他就是在倡議這個題目
Make it possible for the government and possibly related units to understand
讓可能政府還有可能相關的單位去理解說
is it possible to sit here
是不是在這上面可以在座的
raise the bar higher
把門檻拉得更高
Let these scams not be so easy to operate on this
讓這些詐騙不是那麼容易的在這上面做操作
And then the digital citizen paragon is what I just mentioned
然後數位公民典範就是我剛剛提到嘛
That is to say, it may be aimed at those with weaker digital skills.
就是說可能針對數位能力比較弱的
Of course, there are some open source or relatively low-threshold tools now
當然現在有一些開源或者說比較低門檻的工具
A robot like Meiyu Yiya or something real or fake
像美玉遺亞或者說一些真的假的什麼的這樣子的機器人
can help our friends and relatives discern what Bush's news looks like
可以協助我們的親友辨別布什的消息這樣子
Then I think what I just mentioned is to preach to them.
那我覺得剛才提到的就是說教他們
Are you checking by example?
你就是按例檢視嘛
what can you see
你可能看到什麼啊
Messages like this scam usually mean that the benefits are huge
像這個詐騙的訊息通常就是說利益很巨大啦
Then turn easily
然後輕鬆轉啦
Then I ask you to join the LINE group that we can't monitor
然後就是叫你加入我們沒辦法監控到的LINE群
what happened there
那裡面發生什麼事情
you have no way of knowing
你也沒辦法知道
Then maybe these people were all raised and beaten.
那可能這些人就是被全起來打了這樣子
Yes, so we actually need to increase our identification.
對 那所以其實我們就是要加大辯認
how did these behaviors happen
這些行為大概是怎麼發生的
Then when you encounter what kind of behavioral logic
然後你遇到怎樣的行為邏輯的時候
you need to be more alert
你要比較有警覺
Just like when we were young, we were called by our mother
就跟小時候我們被幫媽叫
like seeing a stranger
比如說 看到陌生人
let's not chat with him casually
我們不要隨便跟他聊天
don't just follow him
不要隨便跟著他走
is the same reason
是一樣的道理
In turn, we need to make these digital capabilities
那我們反過來也是要讓這些數位能力
Teach weak people how to deal with these things
教弱的人知道怎麼面對這些事情
except defense
那除了防禦
is our own sense of citizenship
就是我們自己的公民意識
In other words, the organization's defense is improved.
或者說組織防禦力提升
Then I think outside
那我覺得對外就是
This is not an attack
這也不到攻擊
It is to establish friendly units with foreign countries.
就是對外建立友好單位
or the whole country
或者說以整個國家
The whole is a large unit
以整個就是大型的單位
unit of the people
人民的單位
How to adjust others externally
怎麼樣子對外去調整別人
to our other countries
對我們別的國家
or how citizens of other countries perceive us
或別的國家的公民對我們的認知
Of course this thing is a bit PR
那當然這個東西就有點公關
The technique is like Google Trend, it is also a public thing
的技巧 就是說像Google Trend它也是一個公開的東西嘛
It looks like what I'm showing here is the United States searching for the word Taiwan
那像我這邊秀的是美國搜尋台灣這個詞
Which related searches in the past seven days are linked together
那近七天哪些相關的搜尋是串身的
Surely this is what Google counts?
那當然這就是Google統計的東西嘛
It seems to be some kind of Blinken here
那這裡好像是什麼布林肯
when visiting China
就是去拜訪中國的時候說
Taiwan is still using the Taiwan Relations Act or something
台灣還是在用什麼台灣關係法還是什麼的
To do some interaction between countries like this
去做一個國與國之間的一些互動這樣子
Yes, then this thing is cross-body in foreign countries
對 那這個東西就是在國外是串身
Then there is Taiwan #MeToo
那還有台灣MeToo嘛
What else is there such a word as autonomy what is related to Blinken
還有什麼什麼自治什麼相關的布林肯這樣詞
Then I think these words mean that everyone already has search intentions.
那我覺得這些詞就是大家已經有搜尋意圖了
Of course they will have access to a lot of relevant information
那當然他們就會接觸到很多相關的資訊
that might be on the taiwan side
那可能在台灣這邊
The unit of the representative's speech may need to regularly check these
代表的發言的單位可能就要定期的去查看這些
What you may be searching for
大家可能在搜什麼的這些內容
and check out what kind of content they might receive
然後去檢核說他們可能會收到怎樣的內容
then go to balance
然後去平衡一下
Have we been bullied for our position on this?
我們在這上面的立場是不是有被欺負啊
Threatened or what?
有被威脅啊 還是什麼
As far as our own true thoughts are concerned
就我們自己的真正的想法有沒有
express it like this
跟這樣子的表達出去
Let everyone search and see like this
讓大家可以搜尋到看到這樣子
So by creating a link like this
所以透過這樣的方式建立連結
and then to clarify or say
然後去澄清或者說
To dialectize the correctness of some information like this
去辯證一些資訊的正位這樣子
ok what else
好 那另外呢
is that we want to use the characteristic
就是我們要利用特色
Want to make a friendly connection?
來建立友善連結嘛
Then I think this thing is like
那我覺得這個東西就像
Taiwan RUSH can do this
台灣RUSH可以做這件事情啊
Because indeed we are doing all kinds of content materials
因為的確我們就是在做各種的內容素材
Let everyone know Taiwan
讓大家認識台灣
Know what kind of place Taiwan is
知道台灣是一個什麼樣的地方
Know the characteristics of Taiwan
知道台灣的特色
Know what is the most popular place in Taiwan
知道台灣備受起來的地方是什麼
In fact, Taiwan has a lot of hidden champions
那其實台灣有非常多的隱形冠軍
so much light of taiwan
非常多的台灣之光
how do we use these things
那我們怎麼樣用這些東西
How about connecting with the world?
與世界建立連結呢
I believe refueling is usually
我相信加油平常就
been working on this thing
一直在鑽研這件事情
That's actually
那其實
I will give two examples
我舉兩個例子啊
One is Gemaran
一個就是格馬蘭嘛
Is Kavalan the light of Taiwan?
格馬蘭是台灣之光嘛
because in fact
因為其實
as long as in the world
只要在全世界
man of what may be the world
可能何謂世界的人
almost everyone
大家幾乎都
Hey, Gemaran is very ugly, like this
欸 格馬蘭很讚喔 這樣子
So actually we can use
那所以其實我們可以利用
everyone's interest in this
大家對於這個的興趣
Let everyone know better
讓大家更了解
Taiwan is a Prospective Place
台灣是一個展望地方
Why is Gemaran's wine so good?
為什麼格馬蘭的酒可以這麼讚
In fact, I don't think there is any need to ask for an answer.
那其實我覺得也不用一次講求答
everyone we are
所有人嘛 我們就是
Hey, am I disconnected?
欸 我被斷線了嗎
I encountered a network outage, a power outage
我遇到斷網 斷電了
right
對
Yes, that's the same
對 那就是一樣嘛
That is to say, Gemaran
就是說 格馬蘭
then we use
那我們就是利用
likely average citizen
可能一般公民
He didn't really pay much attention to the war either.
他也沒有真的對戰爭特別關注
but ordinary citizens
可是一般公民
Interests and hobbies in Gemaran
對於格馬蘭的興趣喜好
Let them know more about Taiwan
讓他們多增加一點認識台灣
Is this a way to establish a connection?
這是建立連結一種方式嘛
May be love without disease
可能愛無疾嘛
He loves Gemaran and also loves Taiwan
他愛格馬蘭 也愛台灣這樣
Well, the other one is what I want to say
好 那另外一個就是我想說
Hey, of course Taiwan has another geographical advantage.
欸 台灣當然有另外一個地理優勢是
Uh, like I saw a foreigner
呃 像我看到一個國外的人
He came to Taiwan to pay taxes
他來台灣潛稅
Then he said why he came to Taiwan to pay taxes
然後他就說他為什麼來台灣潛稅呢
It's near Kenting
就是在墾丁附近那裡
Then he said that the coral reefs in Taiwan are real
然後他說台灣的珊瑚礁是真的就是
Wonders of the world, wonders like this
世界奇 奇景啦 這樣子
is considered
就是算是
but well worth it
但是非常值得一來的
And then he's in some dive master's book
然後他在某個潛水的大師的書上
when i saw this
看到這段的時候
he really every year
他就真的每一年
I still come to Taiwan to dive once every few years.
還是每幾年就來台灣潛水一次這樣子
Then it's time to see these Cape Corals in Taiwan
然後就是去看台灣的這些珊瑚角
Then I think that there are actually many such things in Taiwan.
那我會覺得說其實台灣有很多這樣子
Some features that attract people from all over the world
吸引全世界各地的人的一些特色
then of course we are
那我們當然就是
Do these things individually
個別的去做這些事情嘛
For example, the one who loves Malan from Aiwei Vision
比如說愛個馬蘭的愛衛視界的
We target these people to tell them what Taiwan is
我們針對這些人去告訴他們什麼叫台灣
and then target these divers
然後針對這些潛水的人
Tell them what Taiwan is
告訴他們說什麼是台灣
Why Taiwan is worthy of your love
台灣為什麼值得你愛
So if we say that Taiwan is attacked today
那如果說今天我們台灣被攻擊了
Then change to another government
然後之後換成另外一個政體了
Will you not be able to freely come to Taiwan to dive?
會不會你就不能自由來台灣潛水了
even with a little bigger emotional blackmail or something like that
甚至與大一點情緒勒索或一些這樣子
Of course, this way is to let everyone understand more
那當然這種方式就是讓大家更了解說
So what kind of existence is Taiwan?
那台灣到底是一個怎樣的存在
let them go through
讓他們透過一次一次的
through content they are interested in
透過他們有興趣的內容
Enter Taiwan this this objection
進入台灣這個這個異議
Then let them know more about the problems Taiwan is facing now
然後讓他們更了解台灣現在面臨怎樣的問題
Then this question may affect him looking forward to the interests like this
那這個問題可能會影響到他展望著利益這樣子
We connect with the world monitoring power in this way
我們透過這樣的方式與世界監力連結
Ok, so this is my sharing today
好那這是我今天的分享
that is
就是
Well
呃
is also
就是也是
how to say
怎麼講
Everyone may be figuring it out too.
大家可能也都在摸索中啦
So let's talk about it together
所以就是大家一起討論這件事情
right
對
This director Cai shares with you
這個蔡總監跟大家分享
Then shall we directly invite the other two sharers first?
那我們是不是先就直接請其他前面兩位這個分享人
We also made it to the stage
我們也做到了台前來
right
對
then next words
那接下來的話
of course we
那當然我們
Well
呃
We have prepared some topics
我們有準備一些題目
wait a minute i will keep
等一下我會一直地
How many people will ask this
會問幾位這個
this sharer
這個分享者
then discuss with you
然後跟大家討論一下
After all
到底說
In addition to what we just shared
我們除了剛剛的分享之外
Maybe some answers to some questions
也許針對一些題目來一些回答
then let me respond first
那我先回應一下
Just now Director Cai mentioned several computers
剛剛蔡總監提到幾個電腦
I think it's actually quite interesting
我覺得其實蠻有意思
just mentioned
剛剛有提到說
noodle
面
like our disaster prevention
像我們防災
we will do drills
我們會做演練
face war
面對戰爭
then we will do
那我們也會做
this
這個
Hanguang exercise and so on
漢光演習等等
But in the face of cognitive warfare
但是面對認知作戰
Actually, we didn't do disaster drills.
其實我們並沒有做防災演練
It was actually good just now
剛剛其實很好
right
對
So actually I think the clip I just mentioned
所以說其實我覺得剛剛提到的剪輯
just thought of saying
就想到說
We just saw a lot of scams
我們剛剛看到很多詐騙
It's all about cheating on points
都是在點數上詐騙
It's all a scam
其實都是騙錢嘛
It's okay to cheat
騙錢還好
If today is to lie to us about Taiwan's sovereignty
如果今天是要騙我們台灣的主權
Because we had some discussions before
因為我們之前一些有商量
will go through this discussion on the matter
會經過這種在關於這件事情的討論
It is said that it is better to buy Taiwan than to fight Taiwan
都說打台灣不如買台灣
Buying Taiwan is worse than cheating Taiwan
買台灣又不如騙台灣
Yes, I even think about it by myself
對 甚至我會自己隨便亂想
That is to say, are these
就是說這些是不是
It can be organized to understand who
它可以組織性的了解哪些人
The ability to identify information is relatively weak
是資訊的識別能力比較弱的
then circle them
然後把他們圈起來
Then for some Honeypot
然後針對一些Honeypot
just keep posting the wrong message
就一直放錯誤的消息
and then everyone messed up
然後大家就亂成一團
This is also an attack
這也是一種攻擊嘛
right
對
This is actually
這其實就是
And I think this is what I want in the future
而且這個我覺得也是後續想要
I think it's worth it
就是我覺得值得大家
Not necessarily that we are on this occasion
也不一定我們在這個場合
there is a way to solve
就有辦法解決到
Because in fact, I think especially Q community works
因為其實我覺得尤其Q社區作品
For example we can maybe
比如說我們可以也許
You can get some data reports from some communities
可以拿到一些社群的一些資料報告
look at those who target disinformation
看那些針對假訊息
Maybe you can see some fluctuations in the community
也許可以看到社群的一些波動
But that's probably more like what we call an autopsy report
但那可能比較像我們講難聽一點叫驗屍報告
We can look back when it's over
事情發生結束以後我們可以回頭看
OK, so this is how it happened
OK 原來這個事情是這樣發生的
But if you avoid it beforehand
但是如果事前就先避免
OK, the purpose of this event today
OK 這次今天這個活動的目的
Okay, so then I figured I'd let everyone come
好 所以後來我覺得要讓大家來
how many guests
問一下大家幾位來賓
is to face the war
就是面對戰爭
Then I think this war contains many forms
那我覺得這戰爭包含非常多的形態
Entities really did shoot
實體真的就是有開槍
outside of war like cannon
大炮這樣的戰爭之外
And we are now in a
還有我們現在處在一個
A State of We Call Gray Threat Hybrid War
我們叫做灰色威脅混合戰爭的狀態
As if you could actually say we weren't at war
好像其實你能說我們沒有被開戰
aren't we attacked
我們沒有被攻打嗎
It doesn't seem to be the case
好像不盡然
we're under some kind of war
我們在某種程度的戰爭之下
Then how do we face such disinformation
那我們要如何面對這樣的disinformation
Let's say fake news, fake news
我們譬如說假訊息 假新聞
or Xu A's message
或是許甲的訊息
how should we face
我們應該要怎麼面對
what tools do we have to deal with him
我們有什麼樣的工具可以去應付他
And if we don't have internet anymore
還有如果我們再沒有網路
What to do when online
網路的時候又該怎麼辦
This problem seems a bit big and difficult
這個問題好像有點大有點難
I don't know which one has a way to respond to this with us first
我不知道哪一位有辦法先跟我們這個回應一下
Did he just say you that tool
他把你剛剛是不是說你那個工具
Can be used even when there is no Internet
沒有網路的時候也可以使用
Indeed he can use
確實他是可以使用
But the problem is you're inside it's a closed place
但是問題是你在裡面他是一個封閉的地方
he is a closed place
他是一個封閉的地方
you're inside assuming you're inside
你在裡面假設你裡面
you already have a team
你本來就有一個團隊
Then the information in your team will be released there.
那你這個團隊裡面的訊息在裡面發佈
But that software he is not
但那個軟體他不是
I don't think this is the use
我覺得不是這種用途
he is the use of a particular person
他是一個特定人物的用途
I think there may be something to say here
我覺得這裡面可能要講一下
Everyone is concerned about, for example, the fact that there is no Internet disconnection.
大家對於比方說沒有網路斷網這件事情
I think especially for people who don't know how to use the Internet
我覺得尤其是在不懂網路的人
He will feel that this is a question of zero and one.
他都會覺得這個是零跟一的問題
You used it well today
你今天用的好好的
And no internet means I can't access anything
然後沒有網路就表示我什麼東西都不能上
It's not like that
其實不是這樣子
Like we have learned online for a long time
像我們網路學很久的
The web is a very complex structure
網路是一個非常繁複的結構
let's say
比方說好了
you said there is no internet
你說沒有網路
It's because you, let's say your home internet doesn't work.
就是因為 你 比方說你的 家裡的網路上不了
Or your mobile phone network is not available
或者說你的手機網路上不了
Then you probably have the satellite network still on.
那你可能 衛星網路還在
Or your radio is still there
或者說你的radio還在
Or let's say the so-called internet blows up
或者說 假設所謂的網路炸好了
For example, suppose he has a way to cut off your country's external Internet access
比方說 假設他有辦法把你國家的對外的網路權斷掉
But your domestic network is good
但是你在國內的網路是好的
For example, if you feed Hsinchu people
那比方說 你把養活新竹人
Then you blow up a communication center in Hsinchu
然後你把新竹的一個什麼通訊中心把它炸掉
then the other you are good
那這其他的 你是好的
And then and and this kind of stuff he's usually in
然後而且 而且這種東西他通常都很可能在
after you hang him up
你把他弄掛了之後
He'll be back in a few hours or a day or two
他在幾個小時或者一兩天之內就會恢復
So he hangs up on the Internet, everyone, don't think about it
所以 所以他網路掛掉大家不要被一想
Wow, once it hangs up, it's all gone
哇 一掛掉就是全部沒有
no no no usually
沒有 沒有 沒有 通常
Usually in a proven environment
通常在證實的環境裡面
He breaks all of a sudden
他都是斷掉一下子
or break something in an area
或者斷掉一區域的東西
So everyone, don't use zeros and ones to express this matter.
所以大家千萬不要把這件事情就用零跟一來表示
Even if Ukraine is fine, the war situation in Ukraine is very, very critical
就算烏克蘭好了 烏克蘭在戰況很很很危急
Or when they actually have intermittent internet
或者是什麼時候 他們其實網路也都是斷斷續續的
after that
到後來
Almost everything online is actually good
幾乎網路也都其實還是好的
So this might just be a supplement for him.
所以這個可能就是給他補充一下
because I once had to answer a question
因為我曾經會有回答一個問題
I analyzed the whole thing to let people know
我把整件事分析讓人家知道說
The network is a very multi-node and multi-state thing
網路是非常多節點非常多狀態的東西
It's not that you said that once you hang up, it will be gone.
不是你說一掛就沒有了
So everyone may have a correct understanding
所以大家可能要有一個正確的認知
I think it's important to have a little mood just mentioned
我覺得剛剛提到有一點心情很重要
This is to promote the idea of ​​​​Taiwan Internet
這個要推一下台灣網路想法
Did the previous topic talk about it?
上一個主題是不是就講到
Our external communication
我們對外的這個通訊
Maybe we guide this communication network in Taiwan
也許我們導內台灣導內的這個通訊網路
Still intact but our external Internet connection may be external Hailan
依然完整但是我們對外的網路連接也許是對外的海嵐
potentially sabotage so we maybe
有可能遭破壞所以我們也許
I don’t know if my information security information is correct
我不知道我這樣的資安的資訊對不對啦
Maybe we can't watch Netflix
也許我們看不了Netflix
But we can still go to PTT
但我們還可以上PTT
Because TPTT is a network in Taiwan
因為TPTT是在台灣裡面的網路
But Netflix may introduce foreign servers
但是Netflix可能介紹國外的伺服器
Everyone is welcome to watch this Taiwan lecture on health last month.
歡迎大家可以去看上個月的這個台灣講康的
this activity
這個活動
There should be videos online
應該網路上有影片可以看
then i think i want it too
那我覺得我也想要
I want to ask again, if so
我想再追問一下那如果是
Because like, especially otherwise, it means diplomatic marriage or Q club
因為像尤其是不然是說外交結婚或是Q社
What's the use of the community
什麼用的社群
just mentioned now
現在剛有提到
major online communities
主要這些大的網路社群
In fact, it is an international platform
其實都是國際的平台
Really if we meet and say yes
那真的如果我們遇到說好
Taiwan has us
台灣有我們其實
maybe intranet
也許內網
When the network in Taiwan's own island is still available
台灣自己島內的這個網路還是通的時候
Then if you encounter the external contact section
那如果碰到對外聯繫段的時候
do we have any other way
我們還有沒有什麼方法
Or do we have any method in advance?
或是說我們事前有沒有先做好什麼方式
avoid this from happening
避免這樣的情況發生
or even when this happens
或是即使這樣的情況發生的時候
We can still have a close relationship with the outside world
我們還是可以跟外界有很緊密
or enough links
或是足夠的連結
Let us call for help
讓我們能夠對外求援
I don't know if you have some experience or ideas like this
我不知道你們有沒有這樣的一些經驗或想法
Then I, I, just, just had
那我我先就剛剛就是剛剛有
The host mentioned the question of what to do if there is no Internet
主持人有提到那個沒有網路怎麼辦的問題
In fact, now the various communities
就是其實現在就是各個社區
In other words, the chief and the others can also use advertisements
或是說里長他們也是可以通過廣告
This kind of community-based broadcasting could be an alternative when the internet goes down
這種社區型的廣播可能會是在網路斷掉的時候的一個替代性的做法
And radio is also broadcasting is also a practice
還有radio也是廣播也是一個做法
That said, now I know there are other teams working on the kind of mobile that can
那就是說現在我知道有其他的團隊在研發那種移動型的就是可以在幾百
That is, one that can maintain a short-cast communication within a few kilometers.
就是可以在幾公里 幾公里內就是可以維持一個短播通訊的一個
a machine like this
一個機器這樣子
For the short broadcast communication, you can actually buy the transmitter on Shopee
那短播通訊的話其實蝦皮上面就買得到那個發射器
If he is interested, he can buy it and play with it himself.
他有興趣的話可以去買來自己玩玩看
And actually before the discussion of disconnection
然後其實在斷網的討論之前
Everyone, we would like to bring you to discuss the communication network in case of emergency.
大家我們會比較希望去帶大家討論的會是說就是大家在緊急狀況下的通訊網絡
Or does the network of contacts need to be established first
或是聯絡人的網絡是不是需要先被建立起來
whether domestic or foreign
那不管是國內或是國外
It is under a situation, whether it is a natural disaster or a war
就是在一個不管是天災人或是戰爭的狀況底下
Did your emergency contact person first anticipate who it is?
那你的緊急的聯絡人是不是有先去預想說到底是誰
Or you as a government unit
或是說你身為政府單位
Or you are an information dissemination unit
或是說你是身為是一個資訊傳播的單位
Do you maintain a good relationship with foreign countries?
你跟國外有沒有保持一個良好的關係
when your country is in crisis
那在你的國家遭受危機的時候
Is there any way for units in other countries to take you to make an information report?
其他國家的單位有沒有辦法帶聽你來做一個資訊的
dissemination of information or make a retweet
資訊的傳播或是做一個轉發
Because like now, let's say I also work at Radio Central
因為像現在 比方說我也在中央廣播電台工作
The Central Radio Station and foreign radio stations
那中央廣播電台跟國外的廣播電台
is there to maintain a friendly relationship
是有在維持一個友好的關係
Then when one of the media is
那當其中一個媒體就是
It is when there is no way to continue to spread information
就是沒有辦法再繼續做資訊傳播的時候
Can it be replaced by foreign media?
是不是可以由國外的媒體來做替代
that would say something like
那會說像是
Ukraine they have three media companies
烏克蘭他們有三家媒體公司
Like Oneplus One Media and Starlight Media
像Oneplus One Media跟Starlight Media
That is, they have three media
就是他們有三家媒體
It is an alliance with United News
就是有做一個United News的一個結盟
When they were at war, the three media outlets all spoke well.
他們在打仗的時候 三家媒體都講好說
If one of them suddenly couldn't broadcast the news
如果有一家突然沒有辦法播報新聞
The other two have to make up
其他兩家要補上
All these communications and coordination must be done before the war
這些溝通或是協調都是在戰爭前都要先做
you can't say
你沒有辦法說
I started to fight, I'll come back and think about what I want
我開始開始打了我再來想說我要怎麼樣
this might be a bit too slow
這可能就有點太慢
So in response to the fact that there was no internet just now
所以回應到剛才沒有網路跟就是
These are the problems of self-communication
就是這些自通訊的問題
In fact, we usually have to put
其實我們在平常的時候就要先把
Contacts and our partners
聯絡人還有我們的合作單位
And this information network must first
還有這個資訊網絡都是要先
Everyone should talk first
大家要先講好
It's what it's like when you're on alert
就是在警惕狀況下的時候有什麼樣子的
contingency measures
應變措施
Director
總監
Actually, I think it doesn't matter
其實我覺得不管是
Just to answer this question
剛才要針對這題的回應
Or we're watching him dissect Ukraine
或者說我們在看他解析烏克蘭
Some things to do in the face of this war
針對這個戰爭面對做的一些事情
In fact, there are some examples
其實都有一些示範了
I'm still the same as I was in the briefing.
我還是跟我就是簡報裡面的觀點一樣
that is
就是說
It is to use the design method of one seat to one seat to generally improve
就是用一席一席的設計的方式去普遍提升
Everyone for this information
大家對於這些資訊
There is also the establishment of some collaborative mechanisms for the information network
還有資訊人際網路的一些協作的機制的建立
this matter is very important
這件事情是非常重要的
then it needs a drill
那它需要演練
Let's think about it a little more.
那這個東西我們再擴想一點
For example, the exercise just mentioned
譬如說剛剛講的那個演習
Is it just an air defense exercise now?
現在還要防空演習而已嗎
Or do we actually have to do more differently
還是其實我們必須要做更多不同
Some exercises for different possible situations
面對不同可能情況的一些演習
That or relatively speaking
那或者說針對相對來說
Larger of these influential nodes
比較大的這些影響力節點
do we need
我們是不是需要
let them know they are in this
讓他們知道自己在這個
possible situation
可能發生的狀況
what is his role
他要扮演的角色是什麼
then how will he follow
那他要怎麼樣跟
Follow his people to do some communication
follow他的這些人去做一些溝通
Or do some emotional soothing actions?
或者說做一些情緒的安撫的動作嗎
Or please support the frontline
或者說請大家支援前線
do something like this
做什麼東西這樣子
That may be through this way
那可能就是透過這樣的方式
Do some information transfer and collaboration between people
去做一些人與人之間的資訊傳遞和協作
Just now Jiawei also mentioned
那剛剛家瑋也有講到
Part of that is about government units
一部分是那關於政府單位
between countries
就是國與國之間的
or those links between the State and other organizations
或國與其他組織之間的這些聯繫
actually i think
其實我想
The usual international network
平常的一些國際關係網絡
or business network
或是商業關係網絡
In fact, they are all doing such things
其實都有在做這樣的事情
Just for the general public like this
只是針對這樣子的一般大眾
Have we prepared a mechanism
我們是不是已經準備好一套機制
to train everyone
去訓練大家
To raise awareness of this matter
去讓大家提升這件事情的意識
I haven't seen it yet
我目前是還沒有看到
but just saw
不過剛才有看到
Digital Diplomacy Association
就是數位外交協會
There are various roles for
有針對各式各樣的角色
Start to develop some cooperation mechanisms like this
開始去研發這樣子的一些協作機制
i think its a good start
我覺得它是一個很好的開始
That is, I hope everyone can support more
那就是希望大家可以多支持
also expand it
還要擴大它
I feel like I am today
我覺得我這個今天也是
whether online friends
不管是在線上的朋友
or friends present
或者在場的朋友
Everyone can recall
大家可以回想一下
did you memorize
你有沒有背下來
your closest
你最親近的
Phone numbers of family members who live with relatives and friends
親友同住家人的電話號碼
Because digital tools are very advanced now
因為現在數位工具非常發達的情況
you now just press
你現在都直接按
Regardless of Line Messenger
不管Line Messenger
Or receive a message according to that image
或是接到按那個圖像式的
Can you still remember that phone number?
你還背得起來那個電話號碼嗎
good
好
Looking back on this, I will remind everyone that
這個回頭來 我就提醒大家一個點就是
Do you still remember that there is a way to communicate without the Internet?
大家還記得有一個不用網路也可以通訊的方法
the phone called legacy
叫做傳統的那個電話
Telephone lines are different from Internet lines.
電話走的線跟網路走的線是不一樣的
So actually
所以其實
i don't know what to do
我不知道要怎樣
Compared with this age, it is good if everyone still has an impression
比較這個年紀 好如果大家還有印象
Maybe there used to be a time when everyone in the house probably had a landline phone.
也許以前家裡大家也許都還有室內電話的時候
There is a power outage, and the indoor phone can still be played.
停電了 室內電話是可以播的
right good
對 好
You may know this or before
這個或是以前大家可能還知道
How to use radio
有廣播 廣播怎麼使用
But now everyone still knows how to use radio
但現在大家還知道廣播怎麼使用嘛
So we actually do some
所以其實我們也有做一些
This one, we have discussed some issues related to the civil affairs before.
這個 臥掃我們之前做一些相關民方的議題了的
when researching
的研究的時候
There is also an issue to pursue
也有去追一個議題就是
Everyone can think about the old public telephone
大家可以去思考一下以前的公共電話
Compared with the current public telephone
和現在公共電話相比
It used to be more common
以前其實比較常見
Now the public telephones are slowly being dismantled
現在公共電話慢慢在被拆掉
It's just the coin or the phone card.
就是投幣或是放那個電話卡的
But in fact to some extent
但是其實某些程度
It is a temporary reservation
是在暫時要做一定程度保留
Why?
為什麼?
Those are the few that can stay
那個是少數可以留下來的
A Tool for Direct Talk
直接通話的一個工具
So after going back I think this is a
所以回去之後我覺得這個是一個
take home message
take home message
is a national job
就是一個國家作業
can remember
可以記一下
just put it on your back
就是把背起來
Do you know the phone number of your loved one
你到底你的親人的電話號碼
what does it look like
長什麼樣子
right
對
You may just be out of battery
你也許只是手機沒電
ok you now see a pay phone
好 你現在看到一個公共電話了
ok i'm going to call my family
好 我要打給我家人
then you just look at that phone
那你就看著那個電話
then i don't know what to do
然後我不知道我該怎麼做
no above
上面沒有
you don't know how to contact each other
你不知道該怎麼聯絡到對方
Even if the other party's mobile phone can communicate
即使對方的手機可以通
The other party's phone can be reached
對方的電話可以通
but you can't remember
你卻記不起來
i want acosmetic
我想要acosmetic
Like I can't really remember some phone calls right now
像我現在真的記不起來一些電話的
Subject's phone
對象的電話
because
因為
It's just that everyone has a mobile phone now, so they can check it directly.
就是現在都有手機嘛直接用查的
So it's also a possibility
所以這也是一個可能
issues worth discussing
值得去討論的問題
because
因為
reason
道理
that is
就是
without these things
沒有這些東西的
How do we go when there is no way to inquire
沒有辦法查詢的時候我們怎麼樣子去
hit us
打到我們
Contact usWant to contact
聯絡我們想要聯絡對象
right
對
this is also a key
這也是一個關鍵
I just mentioned that when we are doing research
我剛剛提到就是說我們這個在做研究的時候
So found this
所以發現到這一點
Of course there is another very important point
那當然還有一個很重要的點
Except your own living relatives and friends
除了你自己的同住親友
and your neighbors
還有你的這個鄰居們
well maybe you're not where you live
好 也許你不在你現在住的地方
you want to make sure
你想要確認好
because something happened
因為發生了某種
Maybe the disaster or the war situation is better
也許災難或是戰爭的狀況好了
You want to settle into the space you live in now
你想要解決到你現在住的空間
is it still suitable to go back or something
是不是還適合回去或什麼
do you know your next door neighbor's phone number
你知道你隔壁鄰居的電話嗎
because our society
因為我們現在社會
Maybe everyone is crossing back
可能大家都在渡回去
maybe not that friendly
可能並沒有那麼友善
so i think it's a good opportunity
所以我覺得這是一個好機會
We actually just actually
我們其實剛剛其實
Bowen-Habba or take a few writers to mention that
Bowen-Habba或是拿幾位寫作提到說
sometimes you really have to go out and get to know each other
有時候你真的是要出去認識
know beforehand
在事前就要認識
This is a normal God of War conversion
這是一種平時戰神轉換
We should always be good neighbors and good friends with everyone
平時就要跟大家做好鄰居好朋友
Only in time of war can we become each other
在戰時的時候才能成為互相
is a helping partner
就是幫忙的夥伴
get to know them
去認識他們
Then get to know your contact information
然後去了解你的聯絡方式
if there is a need for war
如果真的發生需要的戰爭
or in times of disaster
或是災難的時候
that's a way to build closer intimacy
那都是一種可以建立更親密
point to point to line
點對點變成線
A More Socially Human Approach
更加社會人性的一種方法
This is a bit far
這扯的有點遠
But I think this is a good place for everyone to go back as homework
不過我覺得這是一個很好給大家回去當作作業的地方
Then I want to come back and I want to ask you a little more
那我想再回頭來我也想要再問大家一點
Just now I think just now is an important
就是剛剛我覺得剛剛是一個重要的
It's a phone number where you can go back and meet people around you.
就是你可以回去認識周邊的人的電話號碼
back it up again
重新把它背起來之外
Well, personally, what else can our individual characters do in a war?
好 個人 我們個人的角色在戰爭中還能做些什麼
But I think some of the examples mentioned earlier
但我覺得剛剛前面有提到一些例子
I don't know if there is more I want to share with you, that is
我不知道有沒有更多的想要跟大家分享就是說
It seems that the person seems to be very helpless
好像 個人好像是很無助的
But we found that regardless of experience in Ukraine
但是我們發現說不管在烏克蘭的經驗
or experience in other countries
或是其他國家的經驗
In fact, it seems that many people can use different methods
其實好像很多人都可以用不同的方式
to demonstrate one's own expertise
去展現透過自己的專長
Go for defense maybe Ukraine
去為防衛 也許防衛烏克蘭
ukraine defense ukraine
烏克蘭防衛烏克蘭
or Taiwanese professionals
或台灣的專業者
You can use your own profession to defend Taiwan
可以用自己的專業去防衛台灣
I don't know if anyone has more experiences like this
我不知道有沒有大家有沒有更多像這樣的一些經驗
Or share with you what you think you can do
或是覺得可以做的事情跟大家分享
I think I want to take this opportunity to speak
我覺得我想趁這個機會講
Let's talk about it, I actually started talking about it on the first page
講一下 其實我剛開始在第一頁就在講說
In fact, from the very beginning we were afraid and hesitant
其實一開始我們從就是恐懼徬徨
and then slowly find a way
然後再慢慢找出路
But I think the process
但是我覺得這個歷程
In fact, most people have
其實大部分的人都有
But most of them don't really have a way to figure out how to do it
但大部分其實都沒有辦法找到該怎麼做
Otherwise, I wouldn't have spent so long looking for it at that time.
要不然我那個時候也不會花那麼久的時間找
But I think this is something to focus on.
可是我覺得這個是有一點可以著力的事情
That is to say, you are actually giving the public a guideline
就是說你其實是給民眾一個指引說
what should you do and learn
你該做些什麼 學些什麼
Then come to the state of this thing
然後來進入這個東西的狀態
Well, this thing is actually a guideline.
那這個東西它其實是指引性質的
that's what you can make you think about
那就是你可以讓 你想想看
If there are millions of people trying to figure this thing out
如果有幾百萬的人都要摸索這件事情
what a waste of time it is
它是多浪費時間的事
Then if you give it a guideline
那如果你給它的一個指引
Let's say I start off by saying I've produced a lot of good stuff, right?
假設我一開始比方說我出了很多好東西對不對
If you see it at first
假如一開始有看到
Then I don't have to search for these
那我就這些都不用摸索
I just go straight to the black bear and report something
我就直接黑熊就趕快去報什麼
you're right into the situation
你就直接就進入狀況了
i think we might
我是覺得我們可能
I think often when we discuss these
我覺得常常我們在討論這些的時候
as if we all
好像我們都
all in one
都處在一個就是
higher position
比較高的位置
For example, what should our government do?
比方說我們政府該做什麼
what to do in taiwan
台灣該做什麼
so and so
誰誰誰
just bigger
就是都是比較大
i think he should
我覺得他應該
The left eye is on very, very simple things
左眼在很很很簡單的事情上
each of you
你每一個人
what can be done
可以做什麼
that actually
那實際上
when each man is exploring what he can do
當每一個人在探索他可以做
when something needs to be done
需要做什麼的時候
if there are some guidelines
如果有一些指引
let him just know
讓他就是知道
Like I can do this, this, this, this
好像我可以這樣可以這樣這樣
That's actually
那其實
those fears or those things
那些恐懼或者說那些東西
naturally not there
就自然就不在
and this thing
而且這個東西
This is how we learn information
像我們學資訊是這樣
your method is simpler
你的方法越簡單
the more common your stuff
你的東西越通俗
The more people you reach, the more
你影響到的人數就會越大
then what we're talking about is
那我們講的東西是
The cases we are calling for here
我們在這邊呼籲講的這些case
In fact, most of what can be done is
實際上大部分能做的都是
People with resources or pipelines and rights
有資源或者有管道有權利的人
Then why don't you think about how to make millions of people
那你怎麼不去想想看怎麼讓幾百萬的人
they can both do the same thing
他們都能夠做同一件事情
That power is terrifying
那這個力量才是可怕的啊
it's huge
才是巨大的嘛
To you millions of people want to say
對 你幾百萬的人都想說
Hey I want to do something for this land
欸 我想要為這塊土地做一點事情
i gotta get up and do something
我要站起來做點事情
Everyone will find his way
這個大家這會找到他的路的嘛
Yes, I think it is really to appeal to everyone
對 我覺得是真的是要呼籲大家
just find something
就是自己找一件事情覺得
can help
可以幫上忙的
then go see for yourself
然後自己去做看看
Yes, subscribe to send a message every month, anything is actually good
對 訂個月發個文 什麼其實都好
as long as you think it's something
你只要覺得這件事是有的
and most importantly you have to do
而且最重要是你有去做
I think this concept is more important
這個我覺得這觀念比較重要
I think today's audience might be right
我覺得今天的聽眾可能都是對
This topic is of particular interest
這個議題特別有興趣
Then if you are from the academic group, you can follow
然後如果是學理組的可以follow
Haba and QCircuit
哈巴跟QCircuit
Those in the Xuewen group can follow me like this
學文組的可以follow我這樣
I think it's spreading
我覺得就是傳播
Why we keep pushing
為什麼我們一直在推傳播
Because the threshold for spreading this matter is very low
因為傳播這件事情它的門檻很低
that is
就是
Uh, for example, you can practice taking pictures first
呃 比方說大家可以先從練習拍照
Practice video starts
練習錄影開始
What can I do when I practice taking pictures and practicing videos?
練習拍照跟練習錄影可以幹嘛
It can be used to collect evidence during war
它在戰爭的時候可以做搜證
Because Ukraine they have a program
因為烏克蘭他們有一個program
they are
他們就是在
Uh, by contacting legal experts
呃 透過跟法學專家聯絡
They are teaching people how
他們在教民眾如何
Searching for evidence of Russian atrocities
搜證俄羅斯的暴行
So you just practice taking pictures and uh, video
所以你光是練會拍照跟呃 錄影
This matter is actually
這件事情其實在
You are a citizen in time of war
戰爭的時候你是一個公民
you can play your part
你就可以發揮你的作用
that or in normal times
那或是說在平常的時候
You can go to, uh, look at the ones that are said to be abroad.
大家可以多去呃 看看說在國外的
What are the channels on social media
社群媒體上有什麼管道
For example, hey, what is Reddy's Taiwanese version doing?
比方說 欸 瑞迪的臺灣版在幹嘛
go shopping
去逛一下
Then or say, Hey Reddy's
然後或是說 欸 瑞迪的
Uh, Reddy is the American PTT
呃 瑞迪就是美國的PTT嘛
then go and see them
那去看一下說他們
what is ukraine like on reddy
烏克蘭在瑞迪上面到底是怎麼樣子
to explain to foreigners
去跟外國人在解釋
what happened in your own country
自己國家發生什麼事情
They have opened many versions of their own
他們自己開了很多個版
There are actually many on Telegram
那Telegram上面其實也有很多
uh ukrainian channel
呃 烏克蘭的頻道
For example, uh Ukrainel or
比方說呃 Ukrainel或是
Ukrainel
Ukrainel
Nexta is also a Telegram conduit
Nexta也是一個Telegram的管道
Anyway, go to other social platforms to tweet more
反正就是多去其他的社群平台推特
Reddit or Telegram
Reddit或是Telegram
Take a stroll around these places you are not usually familiar with
這些你平常沒那麼熟悉的地方逛一下
then you will know
那你就會知道說
Okay, so what if something happens today?
好 那如果今天真的發生什麼狀況
I just want to go to these social platforms to transfer information
我就是要去這些社群平台把資訊轉出去
That is usually to record these pipes
那平常就是要把這些管道記錄下來
Of course, our society usually does this kind of work.
當然我們社會平常也是在做這樣子的工作
Then the first person in our community will probably
那我們社群首位者今年大概
Because I just saw an audience ask
因為我剛剛有看到有觀眾問
There are about 400 sponsors this year
今年大概有400多位的贊助人
So these 400+ patrons
所以這400多位贊助人
we will
我們會
We want to be a community
我們希望可以弄成一個社群
So we now have a Facebook group
就是我們現在有一個臉書社團
Digital Diplomacy Research Office
叫數位外交研究室
Then we start the second half of the year
那我們下半年開始
regularly in the community
會定期的在社團裡面
To do some network defense for everyone
去給大家做一些網路防禦的
Some topics from the rehearsal will be thrown out
預演的一些題目會丟出來
And then there are some Ukrainian ones
然後還有一些烏克蘭的一些
feel they do a good job with the site
覺得他們做得很好的網站
or case
或是案例
We will share with you in the community
我們會在社團裡面跟大家分享
So if you are interested in this
所以如果大家對於這個有興趣
then want
然後想要
In addition to these 400 people, I also want to come together
就除了這400多人以外也想要一起來
Take this online walkthrough exercise
參加這種線上的演練練習
and want to know more about the future
然後想要知道更多未來
That is, if there is some event information in the future
就是以後有一些活動的資訊的話
You can search for the Digital Diplomacy Lab in the Facebook group
可以在臉書社團搜尋數位外交研究室
Then we will do something like this in the second half of the year.
那我們下半年就是會來做一個這樣子的
This is how the online drill looks like, thank you
線上的演練這樣子 對 謝謝
Okay, I think that's just what we're discussing.
好 我覺得就是剛好在討論這一題嘛
So I still have to focus on what I want to express to the government
所以我還是要集中一下我想要對政府表達
It is true that, for example, no matter the country
就是的確就是譬如說不管是國
It's just an exercise, or the training of the national army.
就是演習嘛 或者說國軍的訓練
I think these things are kind of stuck in the
我覺得這些東西都是有點停留在
Maybe a few versions ago
可能過去幾個版本了
Then it actually has a lot of room for optimization
那它其實有很多優化的空間
Yes, for example, the media is trying to educate
對 那譬如說媒體試圖教育
Is it that the general public has no mandatory self-cognition
它就是一般大眾沒有強制性的自己的認知嗎
Or is it actually related to national defense?
還是其實它跟國防有關聯
That's what we're talking about today, right?
我們今天就在討論這一題嘛 對不對
Does this thing need to be a little semi-mandatory?
那這個東西需不需要有點半強制性的
or do you need
或者說需不需要
Do you need to use some ways to encourage everyone?
是不是需要用一些利用的方式鼓勵大家
To raise awareness and discussion about this stuff
去提升這個東西的意識和討論
then i think it's
那我覺得這是
Because I don't know which unit is responsible for this
因為我不知道這是哪個單位負責啦
Maybe it's the Department of Books, or the Ministry of Defense.
可能書發部嘛 也是什麼國防部
Anyway, if you really want to do this
反正就是說 如果說真的要做這件事情的話
In fact, the government can reconsider
其實政府可以再重新想想看
how is this thing designed
這個東西怎麼設計
Then how to let
然後怎麼樣讓
Just like what his dad said
如同他爸剛剛講的嘛
get more people involved
讓更多人參與進來
Because of course I believe that folk power is very
因為我當然相信民間力量是很有
very powerful
很powerful的
But in fact, if you only look at Taiwanese society
但是其實你看光是台灣社會
It is very difficult to gather consensus
要凝聚共識就非常的難
is there something
那有沒有東西是
probably relatively speaking
可能相對來說
That is, the official resources are available to support everyone.
就是官方的資源是可以去支持大家的
Or classify the roles?
那或者說把角色分類嘛
that is of course if
那就是當然如果
I think now some parts
我覺得現在的一些部件
may still stay
可能都還是停留在
so-called hardware
所謂的硬體
But what we are discussing today is more software-oriented
但是我們今天討論的東西是偏軟體的
network of people
人際網路 人際關係
It's actually soft
其實是偏軟體的
Information dissemination is actually software-oriented
訊息傳播其實都是偏軟體的
the training of these things
那這些東西的訓練
There are mechanisms
還有機制
The establishment seems to have less pondering in the past
建立好像過去琢磨比較少
Is it necessary to spend more time cultivating him in recent years?
那是不是在近幾年需要花比較多的時間去耕耘他
I think it will be a problem that everyone may have to face in the future.
我覺得會是接下來大家可能也要面對的課題啦
Because of course it's too easy to buy a weapon
因為當然買一個武器太容易了嘛
So buying a weapon is of course an international declaration.
那買一個武器當然也是一種國際的宣示嘛
But what?
可是呢
that networking we're talking about today
那人際網絡我們今天談論這個主題
How can it be generally improved
能怎麼樣子普遍的提升
How can we start an open discussion
能怎麼讓大家開始公開的討論
conscious discussion
有意識的討論
This is actually what everyone has to face now
這其實是現在大家要面對的
that can't
那也不能
Ah Fa can't be talking about those of us
阿發說的也不能是我們這些人
Maybe someone who is already interested is discussing it here
可能已經有意思的人在這裡討論而已
but those possibilities
而是那一些可能
Originally, he might face life just thinking that
本來他可能面對生活就是覺得
Oh this thing has nothing to do with me
喔這個東西跟我無關的人
How is he going to get involved in this?
他要怎麼樣子在這上面參與進來
I think everything can be thought and designed
我覺得都是可以去思考和設計的
That is
那就是
what i want to say to the government
我想要對政府說的話
because I think it is
因為我覺得的確是
um yes
嗯就是
possible
可能
lost something
還輸了一些什麼
Like actually I think just now
像其實我覺得光是現在
come meet air defense exercise
來遇到防空演習
I also often ask
我也常常會疑問說
That's the alarm
那就是警報過了
Everyone can move, is that all?
大家可以移動 就這樣嗎
or what are we going to do
還是我們要做什麼
I'm a bit confused about the purpose of this exercise
我有點不太明白這個演習的用意
So actually on this
所以其實在這上面
I believe there is much more that can be done
我相信可以做的東西還很多
Director Cai's reminder just now
剛剛這個蔡總監的提醒
I think it's very heavy
我覺得是非常這個沉重
this is an important reminder
這是很重要的一個提醒
Because in fact, we are now in Taiwan
因為其實這個我們現在台灣
I don't have to speak for the government first.
我不得先幫政府講一句話
That is to say, compared with the past few years, we are now
就是說我們現在跟過去幾年相比
In fact, there is indeed continuous progress
其實是確實有不斷的在進步
But I think it's also because
但是我覺得也是因為
In the process of seeing such progress
有看到這樣進步的過程中
So it will be more tense, that is to say
所以會更會緊張就是說
why not fast enough
為什麼還不夠快
Why do you still seem to be walking slowly
為什麼還好像還慢慢走
maybe that's their limit
也許這就是他們的極限
The pace of the government may be slower
政府的步調可能就會比較慢
so i think this comes back
所以我覺得這個回過頭來
Today's topic is Xiao Bo Da
今天主題叫一小伯大
I'm actually thinking about when this little uncle was growing up
我其實在想這一小伯大的時候
Think about it from another angle
用另外一個角度去想就是說
Not so much small or large to some extent
與其說以小不大某些程度是
Kind of like our role today is all bottom up
有點像我們今天的角色都是由下而上
How to use the power of the people
就是如何用民間的力量
what do we do
我們做些什麼
to bring about change in the government
去帶動政府改變
This is just an example of what we say and do.
這個也就以臥草我們自己說做的東西為例子好了
In fact, it’s like lying on the grass, we have previously focused on the issue of civil defense
其實像臥草我們之前針對民防這個議題
We made a civil defense manual of the original folk version
我們做了一個原鄉民間版的民防手冊
after we did
我們做了之後
The Defense Forces of course also have their version out
國防部隊當然也有退出他們的版本
We're all around 2022
在我們都在2022年左右
It came out around the sixth day of the new year
年初六左右出了
do it
做出來
after comparison
經過比較之後
In 2023, the Ministry of Defense decided to make a new version of the Civil Defense Manual
2023年國防部決定做一版新的版本的民防手冊
OK, what does this mean? It means
OK,這代表什麼?就是說
There is more progress
有比較有進步
When the folks made a version
當民間做了一個版本之後
The Ministry of National Defense or government departments may read it and say
國防部可能政府部門可能看就說
well , he has a reference
好,他有一個參照的對象
Even if maybe doing this will work
哪怕也許這樣做才會 work
He is also more confident that
他也比較有信心就是說
I can maybe try this place
我可以也許可以往這個地方試試看
So including the example that Haba just mentioned before
所以包括哈巴之前也剛剛提到的例子講說
They folk our own energy
他們民間 我們民間自己的能量性
Let's start with a small-scale approach with small resources
我們先用小資源小規模的方式
After doing a minimum feasible solution first
先做一個最小的可行方案之後
Hey, the police, hey, some policemen are still participating in this event
欸 警察 欸有警察還參加這個活動
Hey, I can use it in my official business
欸我在我的執行公務的情況可以用
If it can work, it will be added
可以work 就會加入進來
or I believe the Society for Mathematical Diplomacy has many
或是我相信數學外交協會有很多
In fact, the experience of cooperating with the official department
其實跟公務門合作的經驗
will find out that
就會發現說
In fact, many of them are willing to try
他們其實很多公務門是願意去try的
but they have their burdens
但是他們有他們的負擔
have their baggage
有他們的包袱
I dare not jump in like this in one breath.
也不敢一口氣這樣跳進去
So this is an obstacle they have
所以這個是一個他們所遇到的障礙
It's also very similar to our folks who have to first
也很像我們民間要先
as a young uncle
以小伯大
Close first
優先合上
go and show them
去試給他們看
Just say OK we're doing this workable
就說 OK 我們這樣做是workable了
can be successful
可以是可以成功的
They just jumped in betting resources
他們才跳進來 投注資源
Then scale this up
然後把這個規模擴大
but i think this thing
但我覺得這個事情
In fact, I just thought that this Q-Such major also has something to do with it.
其實剛剛我覺得這個Q-Such的專業也有關係
I feel as though we can't just put a responsibility like that
我覺得好像我們不能夠只把這樣的一個責任
blame the government
歸咎於政府部門
In fact, there is another very important role is
其實還有一個很重要的角色是
The role of these big platforms
這些大平台的角色
Well, I think we just discussed this thing today
那 我覺得剛剛今天討論這個東西
remind me of a theme
讓我想到一個主題
Because actually I know how many there are in Taiwan now
因為其實我知道現在台灣有幾個
The international big platform is now in
國際的大平台現在在
Regardless of whether you are practicing or singing, you are studying and saying
不管在修法 在唱歌的時候在研究說
They seem to be trying to provide a funding
他們似乎想要提供一筆資金出來
Let us, the civil society in Taiwan, offer some projects
讓我們這個台灣的民間團體提供一些計畫
Proposal to do something regardless of the media system
Proposal去做一些不管媒體制度
Or related news, compensation and other plans
或是相關新聞 賠利等等一些計畫
To make Taiwan society better, this digital citizen willful
去讓台灣社會能夠更好的這個數位公民任性
Maybe I think we just mentioned these projects
或許我覺得我們剛剛提到這幾個專案
These directions are worth following whether it is Google
這幾個方向都是值得跟不管是Google
Facebook or some large digital platform
Facebook或是一些大型的數位平台
Check out some of their directions for proposals
去看他們做提案的一些方向
Or whether it's the audience in the audience or the friends online
或者是不管在場的觀眾或是線上的朋友
If you have such an idea, you can actually go
有這樣的idea 其實也可以去
search related information
搜尋相關訊息
I think it's a
我覺得這是一個
Another change
也是另外一個改變
because they are more resilient than the government sector
因為他們相對於政府部門有更有彈性
There are also resources
也有資源
can make some things go faster
能夠讓有些事情可以更加速的進行
Improve Taiwan's social willfulness
提高台灣的社會任性
Well, I actually think that the whole scene just now
那我這邊其實我覺得剛剛的這整場下
One thing that strikes me as something to give back is to say
有一個讓我覺得很有這個值得回饋的事情是說
In fact, we generally think that it is the same in the face of war.
我們其實一般在想說面對戰爭的時候一樣
From the very beginning, it seems that
講到一開始的時候好像真的都是
There must be defenses such as tanks, aircraft, missiles, etc.
要有坦克要飛機飛彈等等的防衛
but
但是
In fact, we just discovered through this field event
其實我們剛剛經過這間成場活動發現
Not really, we have so many ways
不盡然啦 我們有非常多的方式
Can improve Taiwan's defense
能夠提高台灣的防禦力
improve our defense
提高我們的防衛人心
then we
那我們
Uh, before our analogy would be something like
呃 之前我們的比喻都會是像
You can imagine Taiwan's defense
大家可以想像說我們台灣的防禦力
maybe like a tower of refinement
也許就像是一個精緻塔
if you really wanna get a gun
如果你真的想要拿槍
the one who operates the tank
那個操作坦克
This operational missile goes to war
這個操作飛彈上戰場
You can go to the very top, the very top of this participation
你可以去最前面 最頂端的這個參與
join our army
就參與我們的國軍
to get involved in the Ministry of Defense
去參與國防部
But we also know that it is not
但是我們也知道說其實並不是
Because in fact, if you want to participate, you want to go to the heavy army, you still have conditions
因為其實你要參與 你要去重軍 你還有條件
How old are you, and what about your physical condition?
你可能是要幾歲一下 然後你會怎樣呢 身體條件
if you can't
如果你不行的話
In fact, there are many things to participate in
其實還有非常多的事情可以參與
In fact, there are some in various counties and cities
現在其實有在各個縣市的一些
Uh, the police units are open
呃 警政單位啊都有開放
you can join the community
你可以去參加社區的
civil defense groups
民防的團體
This may be the police unit, you can authorize relevant information
這可能是警政單位 可以去授權相關資訊
You can join one of the communities like this
你可以參加社區的這樣的一個
civil defense team
民防的團隊
or
或者是說
Actually, let's take a step back
其實我們退一萬步而言
when there is a real war or war
當真的戰爭或戰爭發生的時候
you just have to do one thing
你只要做好一件事情
you can save yourself
你可以救你自己
no other trouble
不造成其他困擾
Don't need other governments and PhDs to help you
不用其他政府還有博士員來幫助你
It's already a blessing
就已經是功德無量了
If you can save yourself today
如果你今天還可以救自己之外
your family
你的家庭
your community
你的社區
Then if they can have such a defense
然後都能夠有這樣的一個防衛力的話
Or at least don't need help
或是至少不需要別人來幫助
If you still want to come to Huazhi to help you
還要來華治原來協助你的話
If every community has such basic capabilities
每個社區如果都有這樣基礎的能力
In fact, we are facing the war we may encounter
其實我們在面對我們可能遇到的戰爭
will be more resistant
就會更有抵抗力
I think it's actually something everyone can do
我覺得這是其實每個人都可以做
you probably didn't think to say
你可能沒有想到說
It turns out that this incident actually helps our defense.
原來這件事情其實對我們的防衛力有幫助
But actually silently
但是其實默默的
learn more by yourself
你自己多學一點
learn more over there
那邊多學一點
Guo Xiang just mentioned
郭翔剛剛大家提到的
try yourself, contact yourself
自己去try 自己去接觸
no matter what you do on the internet
不管在網路上去接觸一些事情
Occasionally post articles
偶爾發發文章
To establish some contacts with international friends
去建立跟國際友人的一些聯繫
Or walk to some physical activities
或者是走去參加一些實體活動
to learn some skills
去學一些技能
Or just know someone
或其實是認識人而已
In fact, it is unconsciously improving Taiwan's defense against possible wars.
其實不自覺都是在提高台灣面對可能戰爭的這個防衛力
Enhance the social humanity of our citizens
提高我們的公民的社會人性
I wonder if there are a few people who haven't added anything today?
我想今天還有沒有幾位還沒有要補充的
OK, thanks
好吧 謝謝
add a concept
補充一個觀念
In our business world
在我們做企業界來講
Actually, I want this first
其實這個我想要先
What I want to express is that this is called risk management
我想要表達的是這個叫做 risk management
that is, your risk management
就是說你的風險管理
If you have a possible risk in the future
如果你未來有一個可能的風險
war is a big risk
戰爭是一個很大的風險
Regardless of the fact that I sometimes
不管其實我有時候在
so-called community
所謂的社群講
I'm a pauper and I don't risk as much as you rich people
我這個窮光蛋我的風險沒有你那些有有錢的人來得多啦
You have a lot of money, you are an entrepreneur, what, what, your risk is much bigger than mine
你的錢錢多的人你企業家什麼什麼你的風險比我大多了
because you have a lot to lose
因為你要損失的東西多
Then we we are alone, he is equivalent to not early but
那我們我們是一個人他相當於不早但是
But most importantly he is actually a concept of risk
但最重要他實際上是一個風險的概念
then you at your risk
那你對於你的風險
You should invest to curb his risk no matter what method you use
你就是應該去投資去抑制他的風險不管你是要用什麼方式
to restrain him
去抑制他
If I were an entrepreneur, I would like to invest in these civic communities
如果我是企業家我覺得投資在這些公民社群啊這些有
You just give him a little donation, give him a little support
你隨便給他一點捐款 給他一點支柱
For him, it is something that can amplify his strength many times
對他來講都是能夠放大他力量很多倍的東西
Then you invest a little bit
那你一點點小小的投資
It is very valuable for your risk control
對於你的風險控管是非常有價值的東西
Then I take this opportunity to appeal
那我這個趁機這個呼籲
In case some of them belong to rich people
萬一裡面有一些是有錢人的
use your money like this
你的錢要這樣子用
is the most effective investment
才是最有效的投資
There are many caring people here
這裡面有很多有心人
they actually look like that
他們實際上像那個
Digital Diplomacy Association
數位外交協會好了
In fact, I think they raised hundreds of thousands of funds.
其實我看他們募資募資了大概幾十萬吧
I actually have a really bad headache
我其實頭非常痛
Something so important to the country has to come out to raise funds
對國家這麼重要的東西還要出來搞到募資
Then we got fundraising and only got a few hundred thousand
然後搞到募資還只搞了幾十萬
Rich people, think about it yourself
有錢人你自己好好想想
How do you protect your money?
你的錢到底要怎麼自己保護
Thanks
謝謝
that event last
那活動最後
I think we should remind everyone
我覺得要提醒大家
Attorney General Guo just reminded everyone
剛剛那個郭律師長提醒大家
To click like, post these various units Q search
要按讚 發佬這些各個單位Q搜尋
and Haba or all diplomatic societies
還有哈巴或所有外交學會
There is another very important unit that everyone must forget
還有一個非常重要的單位大家要忘記了
You can also search for lying tide digging
大家還可以搜尋臥潮挖巧
Welcome everyone to press like, leave a message, share and subscribe to open the small bell
歡迎大家按讚留言分享訂閱的開啟小鈴鐺
Lock our various related reports
鎖定我們的各種相關的報導
In fact, our issue of civil defense
其實我們對於民防的議題
Or especially this issue last month about critical infrastructure
或是尤其上個月這個關於關鍵基礎設施的議題
We all have some relevant news stories
我們都有些相關的新聞報導
Is it the last addition?
最後補充嗎
i want to add
我想要補充
Because what we are discussing today has a topic called
因為我們今天討論的東西有一個題目叫做
very confident
非常自信
We discuss these things very confidently
我們討論這些東西都是非常自信的
Then we need to optimize everyone's awareness and cognition of these things.
那要優化大家對於這些東西的意識還有認知
Of course I think it takes a little bit of self-confidence
當然我覺得需要有點半強自信的
That is to say that it is a bit like the media leading the way.
那就是等於說有點像媒體帶風向一樣
It’s just that Taiwanese people like to line up, right?
就是台灣人很喜歡排隊嘛對不對
So actually I think it should be broad
所以其實我覺得是要廣泛的
Possibly set up some workshops
可能設立一些工作房
or set up some lectures like this
或設立一些這樣的講座
And maybe use it as a marketing campaign
並且可能把它當一個行銷的Campaign
go get these people in
去把這些人納進來
and when these seeds are scattered
然後當這些種子散出
Everyone will know better how to discuss this topic
大家也會比較知道怎麼討論這個題目
Yes, you see, of course today's lecture is free to attend.
對 你看 當然今天這個講座是自由參加嘛
But are there some
可是是不是有一些
so-called network optimization strategy
所謂的網路優化策略
can go and take some people slowly
可以去慢慢的把一些人
For the idea of ​​this question, pull it out
針對這題的想法去把它拉出來
Then let them be willing to discuss this matter with the people around him
然後讓他們願意去跟他周邊的人討論這件事情
I think it's a big topic too
我覺得這也是一個很大的題目
Of course this matter
那當然這件事情
He is education, right?
他就是教育啊 對吧
So actually I would say
所以其實我會覺得說
Really, why keep talking to the government?
真的 為什麼一直跟政府喊話
because I think the government can be on top of this
是因為我覺得政府可以在這上面
do a lot of thinking and do a lot of trying
做很多的思考 然後做很多的嘗試
that's only possible now
那只是現在可能
I think it's more important
我覺得都還是比較講求
What I do must have a performance
我做什麼東西一定要有一個績效
But it's hard for him to measure performance
可是這個東西他很難衡量績效
to him is an education
對 他是一個教育
He is just promotional
他是就是推廣性質
So all I can think of is to do more of this.
所以我只能覺得就是多做這件事情
Then let everyone have such thoughts
然後多讓大家有這樣的想法
let these seeds disperse more
多讓這些的種子散出去
Discuss with everyone, inspire with everyone
跟大家討論 跟大家激發
more likely like
更多可能像
Like this, people like Dad come out
這樣子 哈爸這樣的人出來去
Set a problem by yourself and solve this problem like this
自己定一個的問題 解這個問題這樣子
Of course, this kind of toughness is generally improved.
當然這樣子的韌性就是普遍提升嘛
Thank you very much for Director Jiang's supplement
非常感謝那個蔣總監的補充
Then I believe that today we have a lot of calls to the government
那我相信今天我們對非常多對政府的喊話
Taiwan Internet Lecture Hall will post this news recently
台灣網路講堂 最近會把這個消息
pass it on to our senior management
都傳遞給我們高層聽
Or in front of the screen, or friends at the scene
或者是在螢幕前 或者是說這個現場的朋友
If it was mentioned just now, like Dad mentioned, people with great resources
如果剛剛有提到 像哈爸提到很有資源的人
we have four here
我們這邊有四位
you are welcome
可以歡迎大家就是
provide resources
提供資源
The risk of war inside the drop plane
降機裡面面對戰爭的風險
Alright, that's the end of today's activities.
好 那今天的活動就到此告一段落
Or do you have anything to add?
還是你有沒有什麼地方要補充呢
ok i think that's it we will
好 我想就這樣我們就
This is the end of today's event, thank you for your participation
今天活動就到這邊告一段落 那謝謝大家的參加
Thank you also for this online
也謝謝我們線上的這個
The audience should currently have
觀眾 目前應該有
I don't remember saying there should be around 70 bits
我記得沒說應該有70位左右
That
那
I saw his question, the cheering one just now has an appropriate reply
我看他問題 剛剛那個加油都已經有適當的這個回復
Then Dad also helped us reply on the message board.
那哈爸也有在留言板幫我們做回復了
then i think we are today
那我想我們今天
This is the end of today's activities
今天活動就到這邊告一段落
Thanks again to all of our speakers today
再次謝謝我們今天所有的講者
Then I will also advertise
那我也是面廣告一下
Our next lecture event
我們下一個場次的講堂活動
More interesting topics will be discussed
會討論更有趣的課題
The Social Responsibility of Internet Celebrities
叫做網紅的社會責任
Then you are welcome to come to us again
那也歡迎大家再來我們的
lecture hall
講堂
The lecture hall website is coming up to make a registration
講堂網正上來做一個報名
thank you all
那也謝謝大家
Then we have posted in this message area
那我們在這個留言區有貼上
Satisfaction survey for today's event
今天的這個活動的滿意度調查
Please also help us to fill in
也請大家幫我們做填寫
Then let's buy everyone a cup of coffee
然後讓我們請大家喝一杯咖啡
ok thank you all
好謝謝大家
This is the end of today's activities
今天活動就到這邊告一段落
Thanks
謝謝
thank you all
謝謝大家
you
you